<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The healing paper, or, A Catholick receipt for union between the moderate bishop &amp; sober non-conformist, maugre all the aversation of the unpeaceable by a follower of peace, and lover of sincerity.</title>
            <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3680</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5168</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12898856</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12898856</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95224</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95224)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 384:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The healing paper, or, A Catholick receipt for union between the moderate bishop &amp; sober non-conformist, maugre all the aversation of the unpeaceable by a follower of peace, and lover of sincerity.</title>
                  <author>Humfrey, John, 1621-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for B.T. and T.M.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Written by John Humfrey. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95224:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Healing Paper: OR, A Catholick Receipt for UNION Between the Moderate Biſhop &amp; Sober Non-conformiſt, Maugre all the Averſation of the Unpeaceable.</p>
            <p>By a Follower of Peace, and Lover of Sincerity.</p>
            <q>
               <p>For we muſt needs Dye, and are as Water ſpilt upon the Ground, which cannot be gathered up again: Neither doth God reſpect any Perſon, yet doth he deviſe Means that his Baniſhed be not expelled from him.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Sam. 14.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>B. T.</hi> and <hi>T. M.</hi> 1678.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:95224:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95224:2"/>
            <head>THE Epiſtle Dedicatory.</head>
            <p>SEeing Dedications are become Cuſtomary, I will chooſe me a Patron for this Book, as a Papiſt chooſes his Saint. He fancies ſuch a one will be Propitious to his Affairs, and addreſſes himſelf to him in his Prayers, but knows not whether he hears him or no. The Perſon whom I chooſe to make this Dedication to, ſhall be the Honourable Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi> of the Houſe of Commons, whom I know not, nor he me in the leaſt. If he did, this would be Flattery, which now is Adventure; and might be but a Blurr, which now is Honour. I do fancy that Perſon to be an impartial perſpicacious Gentleman, and that he will therefore like the Honeſty and Innocency of theſe Sheets. I do Fancy, that as it is hard to find a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel to him in ſufficiency for his Province, ſo it is not eaſy (in the circumſtances Speakers are) to have a Man in the Chair of more Integrity (or natural Byaſs) to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good; and ſo far as I know, to the Proteſtant Cauſe. I do fancy that he will not therefore in good earneſt turn off any ſeaſonable well-digeſted Motion (if any be tendred in the Houſe) for Moderation in the buſineſs of Religion. I do think him verily a man Unconcern'd for the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,
<pb facs="tcp:95224:3"/>but not Malicious to Good People; and though Portly, not ſo High as to be Offended at a Mean mans good Conceit of him. I am perſwaded, that in my ſphear, I cannot put a greater Dignity upon him (if he ſerves our End) than by the peculiarity of ſuch a Dedication. If he deceives me, and proves one that deſignes any thing Evil, and not the beſt things for the Church of God, let him anſwer it to the Almighty: He ſhall be no longer my Patron on Earth, nor Saint in Heaven.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Author.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Deſigne of this Paper is to chalk out the Way for the</hi> Parliament <hi>(if they ſhall kindly pleaſe) to Open the Door of the Church for us: but if they will not, to Draw the Latch, and come in our ſelves.</hi> And it ſhall yet come to paſs, that there ſhall come a People, and the Inhabitants of many Cities, and go to one another, ſaying, Let us go ſpeedily to pray before the Lord, and to ſeek the Lord of Hoſts; I will go alſo.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95224:3"/>
            <head>The Healing Paper.</head>
            <p>IF I had any longer hope or truſt in our <hi>Publick Phyſitians,</hi> that they would lay to heart the Breaches of the Church, and endeavour the <hi>Cure</hi> of thoſe <hi>Wounds</hi> which ſhe hath <hi>received in the Houſe of her Friends,</hi> by ſome Univerſal Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Proteſtants one with another; which would be the ſtrength of the Nation againſt Forreign Enemies, and the Security of our Religion at Home, I ſhould forbear the Studying out any of theſe leſſer and private Remedies in our caſe, for fear of being guilty of the <hi>Healing the Hurt of the Daughter of Gods People ſlightly,</hi> which were a fault indeed if I could do it better: but when no more can be done, God forbid I ſhould ceaſe to offer my laſt mite to the Work, in ſhewing the way that is yet left us (and conſequently the duty for ought I know on both ſides unto which were are bound) how to do it; not diſtruſting the favour of God, and many good men in the Action.</p>
            <p>There is a Rule therefore I muſt lay down between the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop</hi> for my proceeding in this great Deſign. I will ſuppoſe them both ſenſible, that an endeavour after <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</hi> as brethren in the ſame <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> is an undeniable duty; and that a wilful neglect of it cannot be Anſwered unto God by either Party, whoſoever of them ſhall be found in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault. The Rule then for Accommodation which I have to offer, in the Name of God, as equal to both, is this: That the Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt be ready to do in the ſincerity of his Conſcience <hi>what he can;</hi> and that out of the like conſcience to God, the Biſhop do bear with him in <hi>what he cannot;</hi> ſo long as by this means, or upon theſe termes, they ſo agree and unite in the <hi>Main,</hi> as the <hi>Eſtabliſht Order</hi> be kept up in the <hi>Land.</hi> It is but <hi>Reaſonable</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> look to <hi>This,</hi> and it is <hi>Neceſſary</hi> that <hi>Wee</hi> look to our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences.</hi> The Rule is in order to the End; and if they will abate to us in the <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> or in the <hi>Leſſer things enjoyned,</hi> ſo much as we may preſerve our Conſciences, and abate no more but that the <hi>Eſtabliſhment</hi> (which being made by King and Parliament re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires our Subjection) may be preſerved in the <hi>Subſtance,</hi> or in the <hi>greater concerns</hi> of it, I ſee not, but for Peace ſake, for our Souls ſake, for the Churches ſake, the thing ſhould be done. The Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95224:4"/>is to conſider well the import of ſuch Texts as require <hi>Subjection to the Higher Powers;</hi> and he is out of Conſcience to the <hi>Fifth Commandement</hi> to comply with their Injunctions to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt that may give them ſatisfaction ſo far as he can without Sin. The Biſhop is to conſider the import of ſuch Texts, as tell us what a dangerous thing it is to give occaſion to the <hi>Doubtful</hi> to do any thing <hi>againſt their Conſciences:</hi> and he is out of Conſcience to the <hi>Sixth Commandement</hi> (for fear of <hi>deſtroying him for whom Chriſt dyed</hi>) to take heed as he would of his life, to put a man upon any more than he is convinced he can ſafely do. When the <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> does what he can, the Law of God will bear him out in that which he does not; and if he ſuffers, he has peace in his Soul. If the <hi>Biſhop</hi> likewiſe ſhall <hi>Receive</hi> a man upon this account, as one that cannot require more of him, leſt he <hi>wound his weak Conſcience,</hi> and ſo <hi>ſins againſt Chriſt,</hi> I do not doubt but the Law of God will juſtifie him alſo in whatſoever he falls ſhort in the execution of the Law of Man. I know the <hi>Law</hi> does indeed make no difference between thoſe that would do what they can, and thoſe that do any thing leſs than all it requires; but the great Law of <hi>Charity, Mercy</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> or of <hi>Meeting to others that meaſure as we would have met to us</hi> in the like caſe, does require other things. This is a Truth to be made known and propagated to the Nation, that all Laws or Injunctions of Men whatſoever, which are not conſiſtent with the Law of Nature, or Word of God (ſo far I ſay as they are inconſiſtent therewith) are void, null, and no Laws. <hi>Nihil minus ſunt q am leges,</hi> as <hi>Cicero (De legibus)</hi> does expreſs it. That is, (I will interpret him) they can lay no obligation on the <hi>Conſcience</hi> (which is the eſſential property of a right Law) as to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance. it is true, if the Biſhop Diſpences, and the Non-conformiſt come ſhort in any thing, the Penalty may be Sued, if any be ſo affected. It is a Law in <hi>foro humano,</hi> and we muſt never reſiſt (This we mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> venture, and can but be in <hi>ſtatu quo</hi>): but it is no Law in <hi>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Dei,</hi> or <hi>Conſcientiae;</hi> for the Authority of theſe greater Laws of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> does ſuperſede the Execution; ſo that there is no guilt contracted in the Omiſſion.</p>
            <p>And having ſaid this, I do not care to profeſs my ſelf one, that am prepared to come into the Church upon theſe Terms; that is, I will come in upon <hi>Quarter;</hi> for I can come in no otherwiſe: If the Biſhop will give me <hi>Quarter for my Conſcience,</hi> and ſpare me in the things, which it were a <hi>Killing me to do</hi> while I am in <hi>Doubt,</hi> I
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95224:4"/>will yield in the reſt. We will, we muſt yield (I judge) upon theſe Terms: To do <hi>what we can,</hi> if they will but do (upon this ſcore, I ſay, of thoſe Superiour Laws) <hi>what they ought.</hi> There are no Texts which require Unity among Chriſtians, <hi>To be of one mind,</hi> To <hi>ſpeak the ſame things,</hi> To have <hi>one Heart:</hi> No Texts, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with one another as Brethren, the <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Peace,</hi> a Tenderneſs to one anothers Conſciences, and taking heed of <hi>Offending</hi> any of Chiſt's <hi>Little Ones,</hi> and the like matters: No Texts, that forbid <hi>Schiſm</hi> and Diviſions in the <hi>Church,</hi> with the Evil Concomitants and Effects thereof in the <hi>Nation,</hi> but they are all Warrants to the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for his <hi>Forbearance</hi> and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration in the <hi>Execution</hi> of theſe <hi>Laws,</hi> when his <hi>Non-Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt-Brother</hi> cannot obey them without ſinning againſt his <hi>Soul.</hi> God ſays, Thou ſhalt not do any thing, which will deſtroy thy Brother, and wound his Conſcience: The Law ſays, Thou ſhalt put him to do thus, and not diſpenſe with him. Chriſt ſays, You muſt do thus, You muſt do theſe things. The Law ſays, You muſt do that which is otherwiſe. Whom ſhall the good <hi>Biſhop</hi> now chooſe to obey, the <hi>Law</hi> of his <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Statutes</hi> of the <hi>Realm?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that I will find fault with my Superiours, or with their Laws; onely as the Apoſtle ſayes of the Law of God it ſelf, <hi>We know the Law is good if a Man uſe it Lawfully:</hi> So muſt I ſay upon ſuppoſition, that theſe Acts for Conforming be in <hi>themſelves,</hi> for the peace of the Church, ſo long as they be Executed upon fit Reaſons, and ſuch Perſons for whom all Laws are indeed to be made, (<hi>The Law is not made for the Righteous,</hi> or the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, ſayes the ſame Divine Author, <hi>but the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteous and Diſobedient</hi>): Yet when they are Adminiſtred to all alike with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out putting any difference between the <hi>Willing</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> the <hi>Ready</hi> and the <hi>Refractory,</hi> that which was intended for <hi>Good, is made Death unto us,</hi> (to ſpeak ſtill in Holy Language) by becoming inſtead of a means for promoting of <hi>Peace,</hi> an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for eſtabliſhing our <hi>Diviſions.</hi> I ſee indeed that moſt Men with whom the Laws are entruſted, do act ordinarily, as if all they were concern'd in the hurt that comes by any Law, were no more but to impute it to the Law-makers, and to account themſelves clear before God and Men, ſo long as they are but exact in putting the ſame in rigorous Execution: whereas there is no <hi>power given,</hi> or can be <hi>received</hi> by any, but to the great
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95224:5"/>ends of Gods Glory, and the common good of Men (for <hi>all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of God</hi>), and conſequently no ſuch truſt is committed to them but in Subordination to the higher Laws of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Gods Word;</hi> ſo that if <hi>theſe</hi> Laws and <hi>Mans</hi> Laws do come in any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Life to <hi>claſh,</hi> as commonly in matters of conſcience they do, there is prudence to be uſed in ſuch a diſcernment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> thoſe that are <hi>truly,</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>pretendedly</hi> conſcencious, and between <hi>things</hi> and <hi>things,</hi> what will <hi>profit the Church,</hi> and what will tend onely to <hi>publick offence,</hi> that both the <hi>ends of Government</hi> may be kept up, and the <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Laws</hi> take place. <hi>According to the authority the Lord hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle) <hi>for Edification, and not for Deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither do I once imagin that the Biſhop can diſpenſe with me in any Impoſition committed to his truſt, ſo as that his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation ſhould be my warrant for my doing otherwiſe then the Law requires I ſhould do, either in <hi>regard to Man,</hi> if he will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute the Law upon me (as I have intimated before) or in <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to God</hi> if it were any Sin or Evil in me to break it: But he can <hi>bear</hi> with me as to his part, which is enough (for I may then venture others, I have alſo ſaid,) and it is the ſuperiour au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God which is the warrant both to him and me upon which we muſt be juſtified, in my <hi>conformity</hi> only <hi>ſo far,</hi> and his <hi>requiring no more.</hi> The Law, it is true requires more, and it requires him to require more, but the greater Law (I ſay) of the Ten Commandements of God, which is ſum'd up in this one Word, <hi>Love,</hi> the tranſcript of the Law Eternal upon Mans heart, muſt over-rule, and relaxes the obligation as to both of us in the ſight of God. And thus when we do what we can for union on both ſides, and no more than we can on either ſide: When we bear with one another, in the things wherein we differ, and <hi>bear one anothers burdens</hi> as we are bound in the common accidents of our Lives, we ſhall <hi>Compound</hi> (I hope) for our failings or <hi>Non-perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi> to an <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> by our <hi>fulfilling the Law of Chriſt.</hi> Be <hi>of the ſame mind</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle) <hi>one towards another. Mind not high things, but condeſcend to Men of low eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, Our eyes have almoſt failed us in looking out after every Seſſion of Parliament to do ſomthing for Union, and they do it not. It is another courſe then muſt be ſought; The <hi>Biſhop</hi> alone and <hi>we</hi> muſt reſolve to do the buſineſs our ſelves. That which we cannot get done by a <hi>relaxation</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> may be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95224:5"/>obtained by little and little, by a <hi>Relaxation</hi> of our <hi>ſtifneſs</hi> on both ſides. If the concerns of the Church lies near any one of their hearts, than his own bare Honour and Worldly intereſt does, he will venture as we do, and what we cannot procure by an <hi>Act,</hi> we muſt force by <hi>Example,</hi> and the Authority of Heaven, and the Proteſtant cauſe ſhall be our Broad Seal for what we do.</p>
            <p>Having thus propoſed the Rule, I muſt proceed to Practiſe. We have ſeveral Impoſitions therfore to come under conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and they are the <hi>Old,</hi> or the <hi>New.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>Old,</hi> there is in the firſt place the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> it ſelf which I muſt confeſs for my own part I do commonly hear, and in the <hi>Ordinary daily ſervice</hi> I do not think unlawful to read. And God forbid I ſhould, when we have had ſo many Holy Men in the <hi>Marian</hi> Reign ready to lay down their lives for the Matter of this Book. If I find ſcruple in reſpect to ſome things in the <hi>By-Offices,</hi> or in any thing of the <hi>Occaſional</hi> ſervice, I will either my ſelf wave it, or leave that work to ſome other to perform. There is next an Aſſent required to the Articles of the Church of England, unto the <hi>Doctrine</hi> whereof according to the ſtatute of the thirteenth of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (that is ſo far as is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly required) I do not find but the Nonconformiſts generally are ready to ſubſcribe of their own accord. I have a few excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for my own part, which I doubt not but they will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed me to make, being conſonant to the Judgments moſtly of thoſe that conform, and contrary to theirs, more generally who do not; I may name ſome of them ere I have done. There is then the <hi>Subſcription</hi> in the <hi>Canons,</hi> and <hi>Canonical Oath</hi> of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which being not impoſed by Law, or a ſtatute, but by a penal Canon; and that onely rendring the Biſhop upon neglect obnoxious to a ſuſpenſion from giving Orders, or Licences to Preach for a year, which is never like to be proſecuted, nor I ſuppoſe uſed to be, it was heretofore very ordinary for many Biſhops to forbear the exacting of either of theſe (which were abated to me without any regret at my Ordination): and I ſhall hope that what hath bin done in former time out of <hi>favour,</hi> will be done now out of <hi>conſcience,</hi> if this Rule laid down does, as it ought, take place.</p>
            <p>For the New Impoſitions, there are three of them in the Act of Uniformity, the <hi>Declaration,</hi> the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> and <hi>Re-ordination.</hi> The <hi>laſt</hi> of theſe <hi>[Re-ordination]</hi> I have paſſed, yet as to others I
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95224:6"/>muſt ſay this. That to be Re-ordain'd to the <hi>Work of a new Charge,</hi> I am fully perſwaded is Lawful, and conſequently, that this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may be eaſily Compounded, between the Biſhop, and him that ſcruples the thing (for too juſt Reaſon otherwiſe) upon this ſaid Account. The <hi>foremoſt,</hi> the <hi>Declaration,</hi> is to be made to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation,</hi> and I think to do thus. I will Read the Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in the <hi>Ordinary daily Service</hi> (which I have ſaid I hold Lawful), and then I will declare my <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> to all and every particular I have Read. And I do not doubt, but this will be as good a Declaration to the Church-Wardens, as if I had uſed the <hi>Words</hi> of the Act and <hi>no other.</hi> I will not conceal from them that I ſave my Conſcience, but will venture it. If it be told the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, I will expect that he ſhould be more like to Connive at that which is entruſted with <hi>others,</hi> than to Indulge any in the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> and chief thing that remaines, which is committed only to <hi>his</hi> truſt, and wherein, if we obtain not ſome Condeſcention from him, we muſt continue in our ejected Eſtate. And this is the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription,</hi> in reference to which mainely, I do now preſent to the Publick this Paper; and in purſuance of my own Rule of doing what I can, I am willing for an Authoritative uſe of my Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, to Subſcribe the words enſuing.</p>
            <p>This Declaration in the Act of Uniformity, viz. <hi>I do declare that it is not lawful upon any pretence whatſoever, to take Arms againſt the King; and that I do abhor that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Poſition of taking Arms by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſionated by him; and that I will Conform to the Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now eſtabliſhed; and I do Declare, that I do hold, that there lies no Obligation upon me, or any other Perſon, from the Oath commonly called the Solemn League and Covenant, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor any change or alteration of Government either in Church or State; and that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawful Oath, and impoſed upon the Subjects of this Realm, againſt the known Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom,</hi> I ſubſcribe with theſe Limitations or Exceptions.</p>
            <p>The firſt Clauſe I hold <hi>Indefinitly</hi> true in a due and a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95224:6"/>fair ſtate of the Point, as it is maintain'd by ſuch eminent and faithful Aſſertors of the Authority of Princes, <hi>as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſaeus, Barclay, Grotius, Sarrania,</hi> and the like Authors: And upon ſuch a meet State of the Poſition <hi>(prout prudens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finierit)</hi> ſuppoſed, I do Subſcribe <hi>That it is not lawful to take Arms againſt the King, upon any pretence what-ſo-ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Clauſe I allow with this Interpretation on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which I think to be the Mind of the Legiſlators. By the Word <hi>Abhor,</hi> I underſtand in the cool Senſe, no more than I <hi>Diſclaim;</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Poſition</hi> I count <hi>Trayto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</hi> if it be made uſe of for Rebellion: And I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by the Word <hi>Theſe that are Commiſſionated by him,</hi> ſuch only as are <hi>Legally Commiſſionated by him,</hi> and in the <hi>Legal Purſuit of ſuch Commiſſions.</hi> It could never be the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Majority of Parliament to advance the King's <hi>will</hi> above <hi>Law;</hi> and therefore, this being their Meaning, I do in this Meaning, (or with theſe Explanatory Limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to their Meaning, if I be miſtaken in it) Subſcribe <hi>That I abhor that Trayterous Poſition, of taking Arms by the Authority of the King, againſt his Perſon, or againſt thoſe that are Commiſſionated by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Third Clauſe, is a Promiſe which I dare not make, but with the Reſervation of a neceſſary and juſt Liberty, both for my <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in any matter or thing wherein I <hi>doubt;</hi> and for <hi>Prudence,</hi> in regard to <hi>Time, Place,</hi> and <hi>Circumſtances;</hi> to act, as appears to me moſt conductive to the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Edification</hi> of the <hi>People:</hi> And with ſuch a Reſervation as this, I Subſcribe <hi>That I will Conform to the</hi> Liturgy <hi>of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>as it is now by Law Eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Fourth</hi> Clauſe I can Subſcribe to readily, as to my ſelf, becauſe I never took the Covenant, (I was convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, I remember, by the <hi>Oxford</hi> Reaſons, and it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Conſcience): But for the Words, <hi>Nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons,</hi> I muſt put in this Reſtriction; to wit, Nor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95224:7"/>any other in a <hi>Private Capacity,</hi> or <hi>Acting in a Private Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity.</hi> It is true, (as I think) that every Man is bound to ſeek the Reformation of the Church in his Place: But it is as great a Truth, that it is not the place of Private Perſon, or any one, to endeavour any Reformation of the Church or State, be it never ſo good, but with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence of the King, or in ſuch a way only, as is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Conſtitution of the Kingdome. Nay, as he may not <hi>act,</hi> he may not exhort, <hi>perſivade,</hi> ſeek, or <hi>pray</hi> in a Seditious way, to have it done. Now, for-aſ-much, as this Covenant did lay an Obligation on the Subject, (in their Opinion) to endeavour the Reformation of the Church, without the Conſent of the King in his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I do apprehend that Obligation in that reſpect to be voyd, and Subſcribe <hi>That I do hold, that there lyes no Obligation upon me or any other Perſon, from the Oath, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Solemn League or Covenant, to endeavour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Change or Alteration of Government, either in Church or State,</hi> by any Means, or any other way, than with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the King in an Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Fifth Clauſe does require a Diſtinction between the <hi>Act of Covenanting,</hi> and the <hi>Matter Covenanted.</hi> I dare not Subſcribe, That this Oath in the <hi>Matter Covenanted,</hi> was <hi>in it ſelf Unlawful,</hi> becauſe I muſt then (I think) be Uncharitable to the Reformed Churches abroad, whoſe Government is not as ours by Biſhops: But I do ſuppoſe, that the Oath in the <hi>Act of Covenanting,</hi> or the Oath, if taken for the Act <hi>Complexly</hi> conſidered, was in it ſelf Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful: So that, he that took it, did as I count, do ill in it, or did that, which in my Judgement was unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. A Combined endeavour to pull down the preſent Government of the Church, and ſet-up another, without the Conſent of the King, and againſt it (upon ſuppoſition only, which no doubt, will be generally granted, that the King did not loſe his Authority in the Sight of God, on
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95224:7"/>his with-drawing from his Parliament, which muſt alſo be ſo underſtood, or elſe, how could they at the ſame time in one Branch of the ſaid Covenant, own the King, and his Authority, and ſwear to maintain them?) muſt be, I judg, a Breach of the Subject's Duty, required in the <hi>Thirteenth</hi> to the <hi>Romans.</hi> But the Covenant was ſuch an Act. Or thus, To own the King, and his Authority, in the ſame Oath, and yet to Swear to change the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without his Will, and againſt it, is, I think, in it ſelf Unlawful. Such an Oath was the Covenant. Thus far I Subſcribe to this Clauſe, <hi>That the ſame was in it ſelf an Unlawful Oath,</hi> and I draw no farther.</p>
            <p>The laſt Clauſe is (ſo far as I know) undoubtedly true; and therefore, I muſt, and do Subſcribe <hi>And impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Subjects of this Realm, againſt the known Laws and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of this Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is what I can, and am ready to Subſcribe; only, I muſt firſt make it Public: I cannot ſatisfy my Conſcience elſe, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it in Private to the Biſhop, though it ſhould obtain, unleſs I Publiſh it: Both becauſe of <hi>my Brethren,</hi> that I may avoid <hi>Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal;</hi> I mean not the Scandal of <hi>Diſpleaſure,</hi> which I care little for; but the Scandal <hi>tending to Sin,</hi> or to wound any of their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences by my Example: And alſo, becauſe of the <hi>Biſhop;</hi> leſt I ſhould draw him into ſome Condeſcenſion, out of his preſent Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Benignity, which he might Repent after; unleſs he be firſt come to a Reſolution of Mind, and ſo acts out of Conſcience; and that alone will bear him out againſt any Inconvenience, that can enſue: And more-over, becauſe of <hi>my own Soul and Temper,</hi> that cannot endure to do any thing of this Nature, but what is open and fit for a plain Honeſt ſort of Man to do. And here there is but one thing in the general, wherein I ſeek favour of the Biſhop, which I muſt explain on the ſame Account.</p>
            <p>I am ſenſible, that a Liberty of Subſcribing this Declaration, or ſubmitting to any Impoſition in our <hi>own Senſe</hi> or <hi>Interpretation,</hi> is a Favour ſignifies nothing: For, no Man that acts in Judgment and Conſcience, can make any Interpretation of a Law or Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95224:8"/>but what he believes to be the Meaning of the Law-giver: If I am not ſatisfyed then in that Meaning, I have no other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to make; and if I am ſatisfyed in that Meaning, I need no Favour or Liberty to be given me; for there is none can take this away from me, which neceſſarily goes to a <hi>Judgment</hi> of <hi>Private Diſcretion.</hi> I ſhall not care what any <hi>Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Judg</hi> upon the Bench may ſay, to thwart me in the Caſe of the <hi>Oxford-Oath,</hi> ſince I Publiſhed my late Paper (unleſs I feel ſome Wavering in my Mind, or doubt in the Interpretation there delivered), not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſome of my Brethren were ſo much concern'd here-to-fore, with the Words of one about it. I ſhould be afraid of what he ſaid, if it were in a <hi>Suit of Law;</hi> but, the matter is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in a <hi>Caſe of Conſcience;</hi> where I am to be juſtified by <hi>God</hi> alone, and not by a <hi>Jury.</hi> But to have a Liberty of Subſcribing or Submitting to an Impoſition, with ſome <hi>Reſtriction, Limitation,</hi> or <hi>Exception;</hi> this is indeed a Favour, which I ſeek in this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. An <hi>Interpretation</hi> gives me Liberty (I count) only as to the <hi>Words,</hi> while I am yet tyed up to the Meaning of the Law-giver. A <hi>Limitation</hi> gives me Liberty, as to the <hi>Meaning</hi> of the Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, as well as to the <hi>Literal Conſtruction,</hi> and that is a great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. I cannot Subſcribe this Declaration, without ſuch a Liberty; and with ſuch a Liberty, I can Conform alſo to other Impoſitions. I know, that the Biſhop can give me no ſuch Liberty, as to limit, reſtrain, or make any Exception to the Meaning of the Law, any more than I can diſpenſe with my ſelf, I have ſaid: But, if he ſhall be got to paſs me for his part, I do not queſtion, but I ſhall paſs after with others, I have ſaid alſo. And as for the matter of Conſcience in it, I have laid down my Rule between us, and the Superiour Law of Almighty God, ſhall be the juſtification of us both in the purſuance of it, I have affirmed likewiſe.</p>
            <p>I will here add one Argument. If there be any evil in this (the Subſcribing with <hi>Limitation</hi>), it muſt be either in regard to the <hi>Fifth</hi> Commandment, or the <hi>Nineth:</hi> Either becauſe it is againſt our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Higher Powers,</hi> or againſt our duty of <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi> Here is no Sin againſt Truth and Sincerity, for therefore do I make theſe Reſtrictions or Exceptions, that I may not forſake Truth, but keep my Sincerity in what I do. I declare to all the world, I will not go a ſtep further than my Conſcience goes along with me; and unleſs I have this liberty, or take it, I will not go on. And here is no Sin of diſobedience to my Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95224:8"/>becauſe the Law of God forbids me to do more. It is a caſe decided by the Apoſtle, and yeilded, that when the Law of God hath laid an Obligation on the Conſcience already, the Law of man to the contrary can have no place. If my Non-conformiſt brother ſins not that ſubſcribes <hi>Nothing</hi> of this Declaration becauſe of his Conſcience, then do not I ſin that make my <hi>Limitation.</hi> If it were a ſin to make any of theſe Reſtrictions or Exceptions, how ſhall they be juſtified by the greater Law, that is the Law of God, who refuſe to Subſcribe any thing, becauſe they cannot Subſcribe to all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that account? If I ſin in doing <hi>what I can,</hi> how ſhall Obedience to the Higher-Powers be a Duty? And if I ſin in doing <hi>only what I can,</hi> how ſhall my Brethren be acquitted that make no tryal at all, and do nothing? And yet do I make no doubt of their Integrity.</p>
            <p>To frame any interpretation of the words of a Law, and ſo Subſcribe them in that ſenſe which a man believes is not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law-giver, is a prevarication of the Law; for he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to Subſcribe to the Law when he knows he does not, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is the Law-givers <hi>meaning,</hi> and not the bare <hi>words</hi> is the Law: but when I declare that I do not Subſcribe to the Law in <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> particulars, but on <hi>others,</hi> Here is all the plainneſs that can be, and ſo no breach of Sincerity; and here is a doing what I can, and ſo no neglect of my duty. If any be ready to reply to me, then you <hi>ſhould</hi> have done thus, and been more expreſs upon the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of this Declaration, in ſhewing what we may agree to, and whereunto we are to make our exceptions: I would have that man to know that I <hi>have</hi> done thus, and with ſollicitude ſo far as does ſerve me, or ſave my own Conſcience; and it may ſuffice him that I have broken the ice, or opened the way for him to do that farther as he would have had me do, if his Conſcience be not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied without it, and he can get leave to do it Neither will my Shooes ſerve his feet, or my Gloves come on his hands: nor will my Limitations be the meaſure of every mans coalition.</p>
            <p>Indeed I am ſorry here to be more Subtill then this comes to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. The Biſhop I ſuppoſe will give me liberty to Subſcribe <hi>in my own Senſe,</hi> and this I have ſaid ſignifies nothing: but I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call my ſelf. It is nothing I mean, unleſs we ſtate this <hi>liberty of our own ſenſe,</hi> and know what we agree upon by if. I by a <hi>liberty of our own ſenſe</hi> any Biſhop ſhall candidly underſtand my Subſcribing this Declaration in ſuch a ſenſe as I can, though I believe it not to be the meaning of the Law, and he accepts of that, and lets me
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95224:9"/>expreſs it, this is no other then a <hi>liberty of Exception,</hi> and we muſt beware that we <hi>ſtick</hi> not on ſcruple; when we <hi>agree</hi> upon the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> In the way, one thing is to be put out of doubt, that, though in Subſcribing to an Impoſition we muſt be ſuppoſed to ſubſcribe it in the meaning of the Impoſer if we ſay nothing, yet if we make our Limitations or Exceptions, and expreſs them (with leave to do ſo) we contract no guilt, or are obliged no further in Conſcience than we conſent thereunto and take the obligation on our Souls, as may appear in the Oath between <hi>Rahab</hi> and the <hi>Spies.</hi> I am ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry therefore (I ſay) that I am forced here to be more critical and nice, than I would be. I can be content to diſtinguiſh an <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> and a <hi>Limitation,</hi> but I am very loath to diſtinguiſh any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, between the <hi>Laſt</hi> and an <hi>Exception,</hi> which vertually is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in it, nevertheleſs ſeeing I am breaking my own way, and I cannot help it, and ſeeing the uſe of words we know is to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the mind, and every man conſequently hath liberty over his own words to explain and diſtinguiſh them as he pleaſe, I will in the firſt place diſtinguiſh for once theſe things. An Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, A Limitation, An Exception. An <hi>Interpretation</hi> let me ſay re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires the Senſe or meaning of the Law-giver, and that altogether, and all of it. A <hi>Limitation</hi> requires that meaning, but not all of it. An <hi>Exception</hi> ſignifies a deniall of it. Again I muſt diſtinguiſh of the Submiſſion to an impoſition <hi>upon favour,</hi> or <hi>without any.</hi> In my former Paper about the <hi>Oxford-Oath</hi> I laid down a Rule to ſtrew the way for our coming up to an impoſition (where we can) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out favour in thoſe that adminiſter it: In this Paper I proceed to lay down another for our ſubmiſſion in caſe of favour, when we cannot ſubmit to the Impoſition unleſs we obtain it. I muſt in the laſt place yet diſtinguiſh more-over between the Subſcribing to an Impoſition in the <hi>form of words</hi> wherein it is enjoyned, and the having liberty of our <hi>own expreſſions.</hi> I muſt confeſs, I have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times propoſed this expedient for accommodating us to the Laws, that our preſent Impoſitions might be required of us only in the matter and the End; that is, if we can come up to them ſo far as to agree in the chief ſubſtance of the thing enjoyned, and anſwer the end of the Impoſer, it ſhould ſuffice, though we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed our Conſent in our own words. This would make out Subſcriptions eaſy, and every one could tell what to do for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: but ſuppoſing that this will not be granted, I am put againſt my will upon this curioſity.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95224:9"/>
            <p>Let us ſuppoſe then an Expoſition made of any Injunction ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaning of the Law-giver. If I aſſent to <hi>all</hi> of it, I may ſubmit to it, and need no favour: If I aſſent to <hi>part</hi> of it and not to <hi>all,</hi> I muſt have the favour to make my Limitation: If there be any Clauſe in it that I cannot aſſent at all unto, <hi>I</hi> muſt have leave to put in my Exception, or <hi>I</hi> cannot ſubmit to it. In the firſt caſe, when an <hi>Interpretation</hi> alone does ſerve me, <hi>I</hi> may Subſcribe to an impoſition <hi>in the form of words</hi> wherein it is enjoyned; and ſo long as <hi>I</hi> can do ſo, <hi>I</hi> may offer my interpretation for the avoiding of Scandal whether the Miniſters of the Law are willing or not, they muſt receive me. In the laſt caſe; when an <hi>Exception</hi> is need-full, <hi>I</hi> cannot (<hi>I</hi> think) Subſcribe to the form of words without prevaricating with the Law, and they that Adminiſter the Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may (and <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe will) refuſe me the licenſe of uſing my own expreſſions: In the middle caſe, wherein <hi>I</hi> have need of a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation</hi> (which I accounts leſs than an <hi>Exception,</hi> and more than an <hi>Interpretation</hi>) <hi>I</hi> may Subſcribe (<hi>I</hi> think) to the <hi>words,</hi> becauſe there is a truth in the words with my ſenſe, and my ſenſe is the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Law giver; only becauſe <hi>I</hi> cannot ſubſcribe to <hi>all</hi> their meaning, <hi>I</hi> muſt have favour to expreſs my <hi>Limitations,</hi> or reſtraint of the words to that ſenſe, or elſe <hi>I</hi> cannot Subſcribe them (<hi>I</hi> account) with faithfulneſs: but if <hi>I</hi> have the liberty to do ſo, <hi>I</hi> am (<hi>I</hi> think) to ſteel my mind againſt all Scruple; and if any comes into it, to caſt it out. The Conſideration of that one Text alone <hi>Be not righteous over much,</hi> will bear me out (<hi>I</hi> apprehend) in ſuch a Subſcription.</p>
            <p>To be yet Clearer, if <hi>I</hi> can be poſſible, If by a <hi>Liberty of my own Senſe</hi> (which <hi>I</hi> ſuppoſe the Biſhop will give me) he ſhall under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand my giving the ſenſe of the Law, or declaring what I believe to be the meaning of the Law-giver, and then Subſcribing to the Impoſition in that Senſe, which is a proper <hi>Interpretation,</hi> here is no advantage to me, or favour, but what <hi>I</hi> may take my ſelf: If he ſhall underſtand my declaring a ſenſe of my own, though <hi>I</hi> believe it not to be the Senſe of the Impoſer, this is a great favour; but <hi>I</hi> ſee not how <hi>I</hi> can be Subſcribe to the <hi>words</hi> of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and he will not give me leave for all this, to Subſcribe in any other <hi>form:</hi> If he ſhall underſtand my Subſcribing ſo far as <hi>I</hi> can to the ſenſe in the words enjoyned, with liberty of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction of them to this meaning (which vertually includes an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt what <hi>I</hi> cannot aſſent unto), here <hi>I</hi> do humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95224:10"/>both, that I may Conſcionably Subſcribe, and he be ſatisfied in the matter. If we be tyed to the Meaning of the Law-giver every jot, the way is too <hi>Streight:</hi> To frame to our ſelves any Meaning without Regard to the Law giver's is a Way too <hi>Wide:</hi> But to Subſcribe to the Meaning of the Impoſer ſo far as I can, and to forbear in what I cannot, is the Way which I think ſafe, and which I ſeek in this Paper. Only I muſt add one thing after this, that where there is no Form of Words impoſed, the Liberty of a <hi>Limitation</hi> and of an <hi>Exception</hi> comes to one; and as I now diſtinguiſh theſe <hi>two Words,</hi> I may again confound them, according to my occaſion.</p>
            <p>Having thus diſtinguiſhed then between an <hi>Interpretation</hi> and a <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> or <hi>Exception,</hi> I muſt yet proceed ſo far as I do go, to apply the ſame to my preſent Subſcription, that I may avoid all miſtake and ambiguity, and Conſequently the laying a ſtumbling block be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Clauſe I do not Subſcribe to the propoſition which it contains <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally</hi> but <hi>Indefinitely,</hi> To wit, with the <hi>Reſtriction</hi> of it to ſuch a prudential ſtate of the queſtion as may be gathered out of ſuch Authors I have named. It becomes a <hi>Loyall Subject</hi> to Subſcribe that Tenet, and it becomes an <hi>Honeſt-man</hi> to Subſcribe it no further, or no otherwiſe, than ſuch learned and excellent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon ſtudy, were able to maintain it. There are ſeveral caſes which are put by themſelves by way of Limitation of it, yet ſo long as we may believe, that none of them came into the Minds of the Majority of Parliament in paſſing the Law, and there were Actually none of them as could be put in regard to our preſent King, we are to look upon it as the Intent of the Act, that we ſhould conſequently object no ſuch Caſes to our ſelves in Subſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to this Clauſe; ſo that, though I here uſe my Liberty of <hi>Reſtriction</hi> in regard to <hi>Others</hi> (which I muſt tell) I might be content my ſelf (as I ſuppoſe in the <hi>Oxford-Oath</hi>) with an <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation</hi> only. Nay, I do not need any of this Caution at all, in regard to Soveraign Majeſty it ſelf, but in regard to thoſe that are at his Commandment. For, let me underſtand by <hi>Taking Arms,</hi> the Raiſing an Army, or a War (which I take to be the true Senſe in Conſtruction of Law), and by <hi>the King,</hi> his own Sacred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon only: There is no Caſe I know, but I may Subſcribe, That to take Arms againſt the King is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally</hi> Unlawful.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:95224:10"/>
            <p>In the Second Clauſe I am more fully perſwaded, that I do of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the true Senſe of the Acts, Of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> and that at <hi>Oxford</hi> in reference to the Poſition which is Renounced; and I am ſorry at my Heart to ſee it poſſible for ſo many of Judgment and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per as there are, to be capable of any ſuch Pre-occupation of Mind, as to harbour once the Thought of another Interpretation, which cannot be made but by ſuppoſing it the very Intent of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament in thoſe Acts, to advance an <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Authority in the King above the true <hi>Regal</hi> Power he hath by <hi>Law:</hi> And yet hath the late Diſcourſes of People about the <hi>Teſt</hi> and later Matters, with Stories thereunto appertaining, brought ſuch a <hi>Jaundiſe</hi> on our Imaginations, that makes every thing look <hi>Yellow</hi> and <hi>Jealouſly</hi> to us, as we even quite forget that the Meaning of theſe Acts is, and muſt be, the Senſe, Mind, or Purpoſe of the Parliament, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Part of both Houſe <hi>at the time</hi> when they paſſed them, and that is, when there was not the leaſt Breath of any ſuch thing as an <hi>Arbitrary Government</hi> talked of, or ſuſpected by any. It is plain enough, there was in the Prevailing Part, (I ſay not in the Major Number, which is againſt Reaſon and Charity to think) an inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate Reſolution to ſuppreſs one ſort of Men they hated, which are now the Non-conformiſts, and that indeed was all the Plot in that time which was going. For let us ſuppoſe ſuch a Queſtion had bin propoſed at the paſſing theſe Acts, Whether the King ſhould have a Power for the time to come, to raiſe Money and make Laws without a Parliament? Can any Man's Heart ſerve him to believe, that ſuch a Motion would have bin en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, or ſuch a Vote by any Means under Heaven have bin obtained (or could be yet) from the <hi>Majority</hi> of both Houſes? To put the Queſtion, Whether by <hi>thoſe Commiſſionated</hi> by the King in this Clauſe of the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> and that of the <hi>Oxford-Oath,</hi> is meant any but the <hi>Legally Commiſſionated,</hi> or ſuch as can juſtify their Commiſſions and Actings by Law, is all one in good earneſt with the Knowing, as to put <hi>this ſaid</hi> Queſtion. And how then does any Man that underſtands (and conſiders that he underſtands) him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, make a doubt of my Interpretation? It hath bin talked, that when it was endeavoured by ſome in the Upper Hoſe, to put the Word <hi>Legally</hi> into the <hi>Teſt</hi> at the time when <hi>that</hi> was in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation, it was refuſed: But what of that, ſuppoſing it were true? Muſt this be the Reaſon on Neceſſity, becauſe they intended to make the Government Arbitrary? I am given to underſtand, <hi>for
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95224:11"/>certain,</hi> that when this Clauſe came into motion, they did unanimouſly Vote, that by the <hi>Commiſſionated,</hi> the <hi>Legally Commiſſionated,</hi> and nothing elſe was to be underſtood, without any Contradiction: So that the Reaſon why they put not in that Word, <hi>Legally,</hi> could not be becauſe they had another Meaning, but becauſe this Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning was ſo manifeſt, ſo undoubted, and yielded by all, that there was no need to do it; As alſo, leſt by the Inſertion of more than needs, they might give occaſion to People for the time to come of queſtioning ſtill the <hi>Legality</hi> of the King's <hi>Commiſſions.</hi> So eaſily are we miſled by <hi>Reports,</hi> which are always <hi>Partial,</hi> &amp; often <hi>miſtaken.</hi> Nay, what if it were in the Thoughts of ſome <hi>Court Flatterers,</hi> who are not alwayes the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Friends,</hi> to advance the <hi>Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> above its due Height? Did we not ſee, that as ſoon as this Suſpition did but enter in the Thoughts of a few, what a ſtir it this Teſt was but in the Upper Houſe only, there is no force at all in the Argument, what a few Men at <hi>ſuch a diſtance</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving (if they were): ſo long as it is not to be imagined that the Major Part of both Houſes, <hi>at the time</hi> when the Acts were made, had the leaſt Intention, or Thought of any ſuch matter. I will add, that I am aſſured for my own part by certain Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that the King himſelf hath ſaid it more than once, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his Publick Speeches which may be thought Popular, but in his Private Retirement upon apt Occaſions, that he really deſired and ſought no more than his juſt Prerogative, without Intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the Peoples Liberty. As he <hi>needed not,</hi> ſo he <hi>would not</hi> have ſaid this to ſome upon the Occaſion I know, if he was not Cordial in it. And if he ſhould be of another Mind more lately (which it were a Wickedneſs in us to think), yet were that nothing as to the Acts of Parliament which have bin ſo long paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Nay, that I may cut off this very Suggeſtion alſo, <hi>Duke Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dardale</hi> in his Speech to the Convention of Eſtates at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> now muſt lately, <hi>July</hi> 1678. hath theſe Words. <hi>Majeſty hath theſe Eighteen Years in all his Kingdoms, ſolemnly profeſſed his Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of Arbitrary Government, his Ruling by the Law, and his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Care to preſerve the Liberty and Property of his Subjects.</hi> I ſhould not, I muſt confeſs, inculcate this thus much, but in regard to the <hi>Oxford-Oath,</hi> and that the <hi>Conſcience</hi> of a Man is indeed as tender a Point as the <hi>Throne</hi> of a <hi>King.</hi> For, as for this <hi>Subſcription</hi> alone, if any can be of another mind yet, he may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95224:11"/>put in his Particular Exception, and ſay, I Subſcribe to it as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to <hi>Reſiſt</hi> any Commiſſionated by the King, if their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions be according to Law: if they be not, I hold the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary.</p>
            <p>In the Third Clauſe I have one thing to remember, which is to declare, that I apprehend not that any Man by his Subſcribing to <hi>conform to the Liturgy,</hi> does engage, or ſtand engaged becauſe of that, to forſake his Brethren preſently who conform not, and come no more amongſt them; or that he does debar himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Benefit to hear them, or deprive others of his Labours to Preach with them, at leaſt if ſome of the Common-Prayer will but be ſuffered to be read by him. I underſtand no ſuch matter by it: if any others do, I enter my Exception. For, as I am one that have ordinarily gone to my Pariſh-Church, not only joyning in the Publick Prayers, but receiving the Sacrament there, and never yet elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, though I am a Non-conformiſt: So, if I ſhall conform (that is, ſo far as I can (which does but fix me ſo much more firm in that wherein I conform not), I intend not but to be the ſame Man ſtill, as to the keeping in with my Brethren, and to do as I did; which is to be ſometimes with them, and for the moſt part with the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Congregation. I am convinced, that it is a great Fault of the Non-conformiſt and Conformiſt both, who fear God, that they keep no more Fellowſhip with one another, which were the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt way to make up Difference, and to underſtand better what is to be done by both for the Peace of the Church, and for the Sake of our Religion. And here I muſt advance a little in this Clauſe; I think it enough for a Licenſe to Preach, to Subſcribe the ſame with the mentioned Limitations: but if I ſhould find in my heart to take upon me a Parochial Charge, it were more fit, and in order to that Work, to Subſcribe more ſtrictly. In ſhort, So far as I <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> ſo far <hi>I</hi> an ſay, <hi>I will Conform.</hi> For this is uniforme, and that I may be expreſs in that I do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſtands me upon; I am come to an Agreement, upon Treaty, to change this Clauſe thus, which differs little in the Import.</p>
            <p>The Third Clauſe is a Promiſe, as I take it, to Read Common Prayer, which I am not againſt; and do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Subſcribe, That if I have a Publick Charge, or Cure of Souls, <hi>I Shall</hi> in the ordinary Lord's-Day Service, by my ſelf, or by an Aſſiſtant, according to the Uſage of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95224:12"/>Church, <hi>conform to the Liturgy of the Church</hi> of England, <hi>as it is now by Law Eſtabliſhed.</hi> Only, if upon any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (or Reaſon) I ſhall ſometimes ſhorten the Work, I will not be held a Breaker of my Promiſe for that: Nor ſhall the Omiſſion of another, be laid to my Charge.</p>
            <p>In the Fourth Clauſe there is ſome Diſtinction, and my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictions or Limitation on that Diſtinction. I will add here ſome few Words for Explication of the Reſtrictions. I do ſay, there lyes no <hi>Obligation</hi> from the <hi>Covenant</hi> on <hi>any Perſon</hi> [in a Private Capacity, or Acting in a Private Capacity] <hi>to endeavour any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of Government.</hi> By which Words I underſtand not only an <hi>Exception</hi> to ſuch who are Public Perſons that Act in Parliament, which I expreſs in the firſt Words <hi>[in a Private Capacity]</hi> but to all others likewiſe, Acting in ſuch a way, as (or in no other way than) is warrantable by the Conſtitution of the Land, which I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs in the Word ſuperadded [or <hi>Acting in a private Capacity</hi>]. The <hi>Government</hi> of this Nation is a <hi>Mixt</hi> Government, and there is ſomething of it in the Hands of the <hi>Popularity.</hi> The People may chooſe their Repreſentatives for Parliament, and tell them what they would have done, and perſwade them to endeavour it, and Petition both Houſes for it (nay, they Vote in them), and in all this, Act, I count in a <hi>Publick Capacity</hi> though <hi>Private Perſons,</hi> ſo long as they do Act by <hi>Vertue</hi> of the <hi>Conſtitution.</hi> I muſt <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> likewiſe, if any ſeek the <hi>Reformation of the Church,</hi> or any other Good for the Nation, in <hi>Praying</hi> to God for it, or <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (ſuppoſe one Preaching to the Houſes) and <hi>Perſwading</hi> to it, and the like (if you ſcrue up the Word <hi>Endeavour</hi> to that Height), with the purpoſe only of having it done in an orderly way, by a due Proceeding in Parliament, <hi>that this is to be held Equivalent,</hi> becauſe whatſoever is done this way, is warranted (I ſay) be the Conſtitution. I dare not then deny, but there does lye an Obligation on every Man in the <hi>Parliament</hi> as <hi>Publick Perſons,</hi> and on all <hi>Private Perſons</hi> likewiſe, ſo far as they can act in a <hi>Publick Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi> thereunto, to Honour God, in ſeeking the Reformation of the Church, and the Publick Good: But I Subſcribe, that there lyes no Obligation from the Covenant upon <hi>my ſelf or any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> to endeavour the ſame any otherwiſe but in a <hi>Political Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi> that is only as it can be obtained by a Rightful Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. If any think, I have not expreſſed thus much aptly or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95224:12"/>fully enough in its place, let him mend it to his own Mind who has occaſion for it: If ſuffices me, (as I have for the general once inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated) if I have here and there together (as Maſter of my own Senſe and Explanations), delivered my ſelf from Scruple.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Fift</hi> Clauſe, I do the like as in the <hi>fourth,</hi> and then give my reaſon why I Subſcribe upon the Reſtriction. I dare not ſay that nothing in the Covenant is Lawfull or Obligatory, They covenanted againſt Schiſme, Popery, to Repent and amend their lives; This muſt oblige thoſe that took it. Nay I dare no ſay that it is <hi>unlawfull</hi> top make <hi>any change of Government.</hi> The power of the Keyes is committed by Chriſt to the Miniſter, or his own Officers; The Biſhop commits them to the Chancellour, who is a Lay man, and yet executes that Charge. Who does doubt but if the Government were changed in this point, it were <hi>lawfull?</hi> Nay I do not ſay that a <hi>change</hi> of the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> it ſelf, of the Arch-biſhop and Dioceſan Biſhop inveſted with the ſole power of Ordination and Juridiction into the <hi>Primitive Epiſcopacy,</hi> act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing along in theſe things with the Presbyters, is <hi>in it ſelf unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> but that it lyes in the power of a Parliament (if they pleaſe) to do it. When I do then thus put in my exception as to the <hi>Matter Covenanted</hi> (even the Alteration of Government) <hi>preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered,</hi> and reſt my ſelf only in ſhewing how this Oath in the <hi>Act of Covenanting</hi> was indeed in the <hi>Complex conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> (in regard to that matter) obivouſly <hi>unlawfull</hi> as I judge, and give my Reaſon: if this ſhall content the Biſhop and ſerve my turn, I may have cauſe to acknowledge his candour, but none of my brethren have any, to be offended at me for what I do.</p>
            <p>In the laſt Clauſe I find no need of any Exception or Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</p>
            <p>That which remaines therefore now in regard to this Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is only to put my had to my Paper, which if I obtain hereby the uſe of my Miniſtry (and none can convince me of ſin in it) I am content to do: If I obtain it not, if ſhall ſuffice me to have made the tryal, and the matter ſhall be all one in point of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity between God and my ſoul, as if I were clear altogether, and had put no name at all to it. <hi>J, H.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much then for the Subſcription. <hi>I</hi> have offered my <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>I</hi> have proceeded to <hi>Practiſe;</hi> which <hi>I</hi> have done in the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral,</hi> and in this <hi>Particular. I</hi> have no more to ſay of that. Of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95224:13"/>the former, the <hi>General,</hi> there are ſeveral branches mentioned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and there are ſome of them wherein <hi>I</hi> perceive it neeedfull to make yet ſome further declaration; more eſpecially, Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Common Prayer, Concerning my Second Orders, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Church Articles. And when <hi>I</hi> have alſo done this, my work is not quite done, <hi>I</hi> have ſomething to leave then (if it might be obtained) on other hands.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, the <hi>Common Prayer.</hi> There are many particular things, little and great, in ſome part or other of the book, which <hi>I</hi> muſt profeſſe really <hi>I</hi> cannot give my unfained aſſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto, and think, that any man who is ſevere at any time up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Conſcience, can hardly chooſe but be ſtartled at. <hi>I</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſome years ſince, a Conformiſt Miniſter uſing the Common Prayer in his houſe, gave me this reaſon. It was required (he ſaid) of all Miniſters, and turned me preſently to this paſſage in the Preface before the Prayers. <hi>And all Prieſts and Deacons are to ſay dayly the Morning and Evening prayer, either privately or open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not being let by ſickneſs, or ſome other urgent cauſe.</hi> From that time, <hi>I</hi> perceived <hi>I</hi> was no man for the Declaration of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Conſent to all, and every thing, contained in, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by this book; and alſo that by the ſhift of thoſe words [to the uſe] <hi>I</hi> could not help my ſelf. <hi>I</hi> dare not give my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the uſe of any thing which <hi>I</hi> never intend to do. I do, and <hi>I</hi> ſhall uſe at home my own Prayers. In the other Preface before Ordination, there is a difference of <hi>Order</hi> (or <hi>Office</hi>) aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted between Biſhop and Presbyter (which was put in alſo in this new book on purpoſe) when ſuch men as <hi>Field, Maſon, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Mead, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> do hold a difference in <hi>Degree</hi> only. <hi>I</hi> cannot aſſent to this, becauſe <hi>I</hi> was otherwiſe engaged in print before this book was enjoyned, and <hi>I</hi> cannot retract my opinion without conviction. In the ſame place, there is this paſſage, but with more words. <hi>And to the intent that theſe Orders be reverendly eſteemed, no man ſhall be accounted or taken for a Lawfull Prieſt, or be ſuffered to execute the function, except he be called according to this for me, or bath had formerly Epiſcopal Ordination.</hi> Reader, can thy heart conſent to this? Art thou ſo aſſured that the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on lies under no guilt in turning out ſo many Miniſters who were Ordained only by Presbyters, as thou dareſt partake in the deed by thy Conſent? My heart <hi>I</hi> am ſure will not ſerve me to do it. In the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed <hi>I</hi> cannot aſſent to the Proeme and Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95224:13"/>by no means, and God forbid they ſhould be true. The whoſe Creed and Articles of it I believe, but <hi>I</hi> believe not that every one that don't, is uncapable of Salvation. <hi>I</hi> will mention one more peculiar thing (and it is a great matter) that ſticks with me being againſt my <hi>written</hi> judgement. <hi>I</hi> perceive the Liturgy though all its Offices does lay the Notion of the Church upon ſo narrow a foundation as the Congregationall men do, and <hi>I</hi> think that without ſome other Hypotheſis, we cannot defend our ſelves againſt Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. It is not upon the Chriſtian profeſſion in general in oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to other Religions, but upon the profeſſion of no leſs than a true ſaving faith the child is baptized, when the Sureties in the name of it ſelf, and not of its Parents, do anſwer actually, <hi>Credo, Abrenuncio;</hi> Having thus profeſſed faith or repentance, it is ſaid to be <hi>Regenerate</hi> in the Office performed; Upon the ſame profeſſion renewed, when the child comes to more years, it is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed;</hi> No man is then admoniſhed, or preſumed to be allowed, to come to the Sacrament but upon an <hi>aſſured faith;</hi> And none are burried but according to a Church judgement of Charity (as <hi>Profeſſours</hi>), they are, and muſt be <hi>accounted,</hi> to go to Heaven. <hi>I</hi> cannot tell well how to reliſh this, for here is no bottom me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks for a National Church. <hi>I</hi> muſt have ſuch a Notion of the Church (Catholick, National, Parochicall) as a <hi>Polliceor</hi> according to the Catechiſme may ſerve for a perſons entrance into it, and all the Ordinances of Worſhip and Diſcipline be means after to <hi>excite</hi> him unto <hi>grace</hi> and his duty, as well as to <hi>edify</hi> him when he is holy unto Salvation. This is no place <hi>I</hi> know for ſuch a diſcourſe; Only <hi>I</hi> am not willing to be <hi>Choaked</hi> in it, by ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing this <hi>Pear</hi> of Aſſent and Conſent. In the Orders of Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con <hi>I</hi> never approve ſince my ſelf was faulty, that a man does Solemnly promiſe to performe that Office (the duties hereof being read to him) when he is made Prieſt alſo at the ſame time, and immediately caſts off that Charge. In the Rubricks to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, Baptiſme, and Burial, if <hi>I</hi> conſent to every thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, or to the uſe of every thing there preſcribed, I muſt not deliver the Bread and Wine to a man, if he ſcruples to Kneel at the Sacrament; <hi>I</hi> muſt turn away his child from bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, if he Scruples God-fathers; and if the Child dies before it is Chriſtened, though the parents be my dear friends, <hi>I</hi> muſt not allow it Chriſtian burial. Theſe are hard Inſtances in my mind, and <hi>I</hi> could eaſily make up the number twenty, which <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the indifferent Reader would count reaſonable exception.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95224:14"/>
               <hi>I</hi> muſt diſtinguiſh therefore (as <hi>I</hi> here carefully do) the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary appointed Prayers, and Service of the Liturgy, from other Matters on the <hi>By;</hi> which <hi>I</hi> declare no Aſſent or Conſent unto. And when I come in, or ſeek to come in to the Church upon the terms of <hi>Moderation,</hi> I do declare my ſelf <hi>Ipſo facto</hi> a Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt ſtill to the <hi>Severity</hi> of theſe Impoſitions; bearing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed thereby, only a more diſtinct, fixed and aſſured teſtimony againſt them. Nevertheleſs being ſenſible of the Scandal which is given to the Nation, who ſee generally no other difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us but our refuſing to read the Common Prayer, and do think us very exceeding refractory perſons who will not comply in the things we can do, I do reſolve for one, by the grace of God (without turning to the <hi>left hand</hi> in doing any thing which is againſt my conſcience for preferment, or to the <hi>right</hi> in conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting my ſelf with Suffering only and doing nothing), to ſet my ſelf as it were in the <hi>Market place,</hi> and if any Biſhop ſhall give me a <hi>call</hi> (that is fitting) into the <hi>Vineyard</hi> (when I ſeek to them) upon the termes of this Paper, I ſhall not refuſe them, though it be almoſt the Eleventh hour with me. I ſhall not ſtick out with them I believe upon the account of reading Common Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. I will truſt in Gods <hi>power,</hi> it he hath work for me to do that he will give me <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> to do it: and if they will not let me come in upon theſe termes to <hi>Labour,</hi> I will truſt in his <hi>Goodneſs</hi> that he will forgive me when I am found <hi>Idle.</hi> The Nation ſhall ſee at whoſe door the fault Lyes by my experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For I do profeſſe my ſelf one who can neither ſtretch my Soul beyond its ſtaple, nor yet will give off upon deſpondence, or on the preſumption onely that it will not ſerve me unleſs I do every thing to a tittle, which is the prepoſſeſſed judgment of moſt of my brethren when they have made no tryal, and which I would humbly reprove therefore by my Example.</p>
            <p>For the Second, <hi>Re-ordination.</hi> I will here make my Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance and Confeſſion. I will ſet things at rights between God and my Soul, and between my Soul and the World. I am one that was ordained by Presbyters in the late times, and re-ordained ſince by the Biſhop. I was perſwaded into it before I had ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died the point, and brought my ſelf in diſtreſs. I was fain to take ſuch a courſe for relief of my Soul, as nothing could have drove me to, but that diſtreſs it ſelf, which I would not lye under again for the World. Not that I was any way touched in my
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95224:14"/>Intellectuals by it, as ſome that never knew me have bin apt to talk ever ſince, which I muſt aſſure them is a <hi>tale,</hi> and there was no ſuch thing (<hi>I</hi> thank God) in the <hi>least. I</hi> have reaſon yet to ſay this, becauſe <hi>I</hi> know the temper of my mind being Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly and Thoughtful, and ſo apt to be intent on any one thing that hath got into it, whether of Notion or Buſineſs, <hi>I</hi> do not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and <hi>I</hi> cannot ſomtimes recall my ſelf from thoſe thoughts to an attendance on the preſent company <hi>I</hi> am in, or diſcourſe that is going ſo freely as others, which makes my unheedfulneſs lyable to the cenſure of thoſe that are not uſed to me; Beſides that, being One reſolved generally to follow my own conſcience in what <hi>I</hi> write, or do, whether it pleaſe or diſpleaſe others, the Offended (who are commonly on both ſides) may be apt to put ſome ſuch ſlur upon me, at leaſt, while in any thing <hi>I</hi> go but in a way uncommon. As <hi>Paul</hi> therefore ſaid, when <hi>Feſtus</hi> had got ſuch a conceit of him, ſo muſt <hi>I. I am not Mad</hi> my worthy Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren who are ſtrangers to me, when <hi>I</hi> differ from you, (and from thoſe alſo, whom <hi>I</hi> do know) in what <hi>I</hi> write, or act: But what <hi>I do</hi> (<hi>I</hi> truſt) are deeds of <hi>Soberneſs,</hi> and <hi>I ſpeak forth the words of Truth. I</hi> acknowledge, the Church in her giving Orders does intend the collation of an Office to the Presbyter diſtinct from the Biſhop, that is an office without the power of Ordination; and conſequently if a Presbyter ordains any, the Church-men muſt hold ſuch an ordination to be void, becauſe the perſons that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the orders have no power to do it. But <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs my thoughts about Orders are ſomthing different from others. <hi>I</hi> do not think that the Spiritual power, or miniſterial authority is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to us by the hands of any, but does come <hi>Immediately</hi> upon us (the conditions on our part being put) from the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt. <hi>I</hi> apprehend conſequently that whatſoever be the intention of the Church in her giving Orders, ſuch a power muſt be derived from Chriſt to the perſon ordained as is intended in his Inſtitution: and ſo long as we find not any diſtinction (which is touched before) of Order or Office (though we allow one as to Degree and Eminency) in the Scripture between <hi>Biſhop</hi> and <hi>Presbyter,</hi> the authority of one in regard to God muſt be the ſame with the other; and the laying on the hands of the one be of the ſame validity in Ordination as the impoſition of the hands of the other. We do read, that God hath <hi>ſet in his Church, Apoſtles, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts, Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> but we find not <hi>Biſhop and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:95224:15"/>enumerated as <hi>two</hi> of them. <hi>I</hi> enter not into diſpute here, but <hi>I</hi> am one that dare not give way to the making void of my Miniſtry and all my miniſterial acts for a dozen years, or more, before <hi>I</hi> was Ordained by the Biſhop, for that were a heynous crime for me (<hi>I</hi> think) to do: yet will <hi>I</hi> be content as to the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of my Office now, to own my authority from him. <hi>I</hi> was a Miniſter before <hi>in foro Dei &amp; Conſcientiae: I</hi> was made a Miniſter then (<hi>I</hi> will account) <hi>in foro Eccleſia Anglicanae. I</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>I</hi> did ill in my circumſtances to take ſecond orders: and yet was <hi>I</hi> too extream (<hi>I</hi> doubt) in my renunciation, or in the way of my renunciation again of them. If any man thinks that Orders give the ſpiritual power, and makes us Miniſters <hi>in foro Dei,</hi> it is apparent that a Man who is a Miniſter already can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſo made a Miniſter again. Conſequently if <hi>I</hi> have former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writ any thing that ſeems to countenance <hi>Re-ordination</hi> to the <hi>Office</hi> (which is good earneſt my Hypotheſes never favoured) <hi>I</hi> do rennounce it all, and thoſe ſecond Orders, on that account (<hi>I</hi> humbly crave the Churches abſolution and benediction): But if Orders be onely a <hi>Recommendation of us to the grace of God for the work</hi> unto which a man is called, there is nothing in Re-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to ſcare any; and as my ſecond Orders may ſerve me for the Exerciſe of my Miniſtry when my firſt will not, <hi>I</hi> do, <hi>I</hi> muſt, retain them to that purpoſe, if <hi>I</hi> be received (on my termes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) into the Church. <hi>I</hi> crave pardon of God for my fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings on either hand, eſpecially where my caſe in the work crept in to deflour my Sincerity in ſuch a peice of Self deny all as I know elſe what was. The prevailing intereſt of my heart (I hope) was right in the ſight of God in what I did, yet dare I not juſtfie my ſelf, but commit my caſe unto my Judge, implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his mercy and begging his pardon. For when there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing almoſt that I do, but upon a ſevere Examination I can find ſome ſlaws in it my ſelf: If <hi>thou O Lord, ſhould'ſt be extream to mark againſt me what</hi> I <hi>have done amiſſe,</hi> how could I abide it? I will bind my ſelf therefore (If I be fit) ſo much more to my duty, and in ſome kind of pennance for my infirmity, ſhall be the more content that I take that courſe to make my return to the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard as no man elſe hath endeavoured, at leaſt in ſuch a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſto</hi> as this is. And to the ſame end, <hi>I</hi> ſhall yet commit this enſuing Memoriall to Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Notum ſit omnibus ad quos haec ſpectant, me J. H. legitime
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95224:15"/>&amp; Canonice ab Epiſcopo Bathonienſi ordinatum fuiſſe; Quod cum praegrave nimium Conſcientiae meae ob priorem aliquam Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationem a Presbyteris ſine Epiſcopo collatam viſum eſt: Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinationem hanc denuò receptam non ad Miniſterij Officium, ſed ad ejus Exercitium particulare, ubicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vocatus (ſi vocatus) fuero, habendi; ea<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> habita utendi, egomet mihi, &amp; Deus meus (facillime omnia in quibus peccavi mihi condonans) poteſtatem facimus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the third, the <hi>Nine and Thirty Articles.</hi> I muſt confeſs my ſelf in this one thing ſomething more difficult to be ſatisfied than others. <hi>It</hi> is but diſtinguiſhing of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church (which includes the Government and Ceremonies), and the moſt of my Brethren can Subſcribe to theſe Articles without Scru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And no more than an Aſſent to the <hi>Doctrine</hi> (<hi>I</hi> think) is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the Statute. But <hi>I</hi> am one much in doubt concerning the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of ſome of our <hi>Articles. I</hi> do think that the Article of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> and the <hi>Eighteenth</hi> Article in the Authentick ſenſe of them are queſtionable. Theſe words in the Eleventh article, <hi>That we are Juſtified by Faith only,</hi> are expreſly contrary to the meaning of <hi>St. James:</hi> And the <hi>meaning</hi> of thoſe that compoſed the Articles at that time (who had not the Light which is going now) was I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve contrary alſo to the <hi>meaning</hi> of St. <hi>James:</hi> Their miſtake I apprehend Obvious, who took St. <hi>Pauls</hi> juſtification, <hi>by Faith without the Works of the Law</hi> to be all one as <hi>by Faith only.</hi> In the Eighteenth Article likewiſe I believe it was the judgment, and ſo the meaning of the Compoſers, that no man who is not conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Chriſtian Faith can be ſaved, and conſequently that every Heathen Man in the World muſt periſh. For this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant to the beginning and end of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, that whoſoever <hi>believes</hi> not that <hi>faithfully,</hi> and <hi>keeps</hi> it <hi>whole</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled</hi> is <hi>undoubtedly</hi> Damn'd. But for my own part, I cannot be of this Opinion, which ſeems to me inconſiſtent with the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God, and Natural Religion. I have offered ſome little Light and Argument for the ſalvability of ſome Heathen (in my Book lately come out, entituled <hi>Peaceable Diſquiſitions</hi>) that will not, or cannot (I think) be withſtood by the Conſiderate and Equal. I have offered alſo in the ſame book that reconciliation of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>James</hi> which I believe to be the Right. I can believe no otherwiſe, and I muſt have liberty therefore of ſome exception
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95224:16"/>in theſe two Articles (and perhaps in ſome others) from that which I believe to be the Authentick Senſe of them, or I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Subſcribe them. Nay, to ſay ſomething that may ſeem ſtrange, I can ſubſcribe the <hi>words</hi> of one of theſe Articles, and yet not to the <hi>article</hi> (without diſpenſation) becauſe I think the <hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the Impoſers to be more than the <hi>words</hi> come to. I ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily think the Compoſers of the Articles did believe that all Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then are excluded Salvation, yet do they proceed to their Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema here (which they have in no other Article) with <hi>wary</hi> words, which is not pronounced againſt any that ſay only <hi>ſome Heathen may be ſaved,</hi> but againſt them <hi>who preſume to ſay that every Man ſhall be ſaved by the Law or Sect he profeſſeth, ſo that he be diligent to frame his Life according to it,</hi> which is a Doctrine <hi>I</hi> abhor my ſelf as being againſt the ſenſe of what <hi>I</hi> offer in my Book nam'd; the ſcope whereof is to ſhew, that there is but one Rule, Law, or Religion for the World to obtain Life by; That this is the Law of our Lapſed Nature, which is God's Grace ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred under a threefold State; Of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> Of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Of <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> That our <hi>Advantage</hi> over them lyes (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks) in our having <hi>the Oracles of God,</hi> which (including the Minſtry and Ordinances) are (we know) thoſe further (and our ordinary) Means which they have not, to bring Men up to the <hi>Performance</hi> of that Law, that is the Condition to us and them of obtaining Salvation by it. This makes that Advantage ſo ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant, that in compariſon of the ſtate of the <hi>Jews</hi> (or <hi>Common-Wealth of Iſrael</hi>) and much more in compariſon of <hi>our</hi> Eſtate; the Heathen wanting theſe means, are ſaid to be <hi>dead in their Sins,</hi> to be <hi>without God, without Chriſt,</hi> to <hi>ſit in Darkneſs,</hi> and the like, (that is (I ſay) <hi>Comparatively to us,</hi> or <hi>Secundum quid</hi>) when yet they are under the ſame Law (I affirm) in the <hi>Subſtance</hi> for Life as we, and we know not but more than a few of them live with acceptance up to it. When ſome Men will have <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſaved only by <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>Good Nature,</hi> it will be time, and no Fault for others, to make the <hi>Heathens</hi> Salvable by <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> This is not indeed here (or there) my <hi>concern</hi> to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue: But that I have to obſerve to my preſent Purpoſe, is (as I am ſaying), that though I know none that do ſcruple the Literal Senſe of this article, which is, That no Man can be ſaved <hi>by any</hi> Religion, but the <hi>True</hi> Religion; yet ſo long as I believe, that the Impoſers did mean more, to wit, that no Man can be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95224:16"/>
               <hi>in any</hi> Religion but the Chriſtian, which is another Matter (As a Man may be Saved <hi>in</hi> Popery, but not <hi>by</hi> it; He may be ſaved <hi>from</hi> Popery, in Popery, and ſo <hi>from</hi> Idolatry <hi>in</hi> Heatheniſme): I have bin in ſuſpenſe ſtill how to Subſcribe this Article, unleſs it be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the <hi>Words,</hi> with Exception to the <hi>Authentick Meaning.</hi> There is a threefold Interpretation, An <hi>Authentick, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſual,</hi> and <hi>Doctrinal Interpretation,</hi> as <hi>Suarez</hi> has it <hi>De Legibus.</hi> I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore advance here one Notion, which will be received (I think) as Conſonant to the Judgment of moſt Men, as ſoon as they have laid it to Conſideration. It is this, that though I account all Laws in general are to be taken in that Senſe only, which we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve to be the Meaning of the Law giver, becauſe the Law is his Will, and it is not the Words, but his Meaning is his Will: Yet do I judge, that in theſe Articles of the Church, which are not <hi>Laws,</hi> nor Articles of <hi>Faith,</hi> but Articles for <hi>Concord,</hi> that is, in the Words of the Cannon, <hi>Articles for the avoiding Diverſities of Opinions, and for eſtabliſhing of Conſent touching true Religion,</hi> there is no Man to be ſtaked down to the <hi>Authentick</hi> Interpretation (which I account that, as a Man believes to be the Meaning of the Majority of the Convocation that paſſed the Article), but to be allowed (or rather, he is ſuppoſed to be allowed, and to take) the Freedome of a <hi>Doctrinal</hi> Interpretation (which is, any Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Explication of ſuch a <hi>Theſis</hi> or Doctrine, as ſome of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Doctors of the Church, or other Pious and Learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor or Authors have offered to the Nation; or indeed any ſuch as a Man himſelf ſhall tender, which in the <hi>Literal Grammatical</hi> Conſtruction of the Article (to keep to the King's Declaration before the Articles) appears Rational, and is ſatisfactory to his own Conſcience, and much more if it be allowed by the Biſhop). My Reaſon is, becauſe it muſt be conceived, that when any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, Synod, or Convocation of Divines do meet about an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any Articles or <hi>Theſes</hi> concerning Religion, they are generally of divers Minds in the debating the Points, and every one is to be ſuppoſed free in the Delivery of his Judgment, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they come to draw up the Article or Doctrine into ſuch Words as they are all to conſent to; and then if it be Compoſed ſo, as they can yield to one another in the <hi>Words</hi> which they agree up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is to be underſtood, that there is an Univerſal Allowance tacitly granted from all to one another, of abounding in their own Senſe, and ſo they came to a Coalition. There is the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95224:17"/>then of the <hi>Majority;</hi> and a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Meaning. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal</hi> Meaning is above the Meaning of the <hi>Major Part.</hi> The Meaning of the <hi>Majority</hi> I believe in ſome of theſe Articles, to be ſuch as I cannot Subſcribe them in their Meaning: But foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as I apprehend it the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> Meaning, that every one of thoſe that are to paſſ their Vote in Eſtabliſhing the Article, ſhould have the Liberty of his own Senſe, ſo long as he can but agree with the reſt in the Words, or in the Literal Conſtruction of the Article, if I bring an Interpretation of ſome Doctor, or one of my own, which may be ſuppoſed to be the ſame with any one of them who ſo conſented to it with difference of Explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from others, then muſt I be ſuppoſed to have the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Allowance of the Convocation for that Interpretation, which I call a Doctrinal Interpretation. I will confirm this by the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriety of the Practiſe in the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> The Doctors differed in moſt Points, but as ſoon as (through the Expertneſs of one of the Preſidents, famous for that Knack) they were but put into Words as might ſalve their contrary Opinions, they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their Votes as Unanimous in the Council, although they writ after alſo one againſt another, citing the Council for them on both ſides. To this purpoſe are the Words of the King, in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for the Ratification of the Articles to be conſidered. <hi>We take Comfort in this, that even in thoſe curious Points, in which the preſent Differences lye, Men of all ſorts take the Articles of the Church of</hi> England <hi>to be for them.</hi> The <hi>Arminians</hi> with Doctor <hi>Hammond,</hi> and the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> with Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> do Subſcribe them, and find out their own different Senſe in them. I will leave it therefore on the File, as the fit Matter of a new Cannon, if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver we have another Convocation, to be declared, that the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Homilies of the Church are impoſed, and to be Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, not in the <hi>Authentick,</hi> nor in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſual,</hi> but in a <hi>Doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Interpretation. There being a Latitude in all Controverted Points, and conſequently ſome Diverſity of Opinion to be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Brethren, for the abounding in their own Senſe in the ſame Religion, or elſe there can be no ſufficient Foundation of Unity amongſt any conſiderable Number of Men of Free Judgments in the World.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, if the caſe be put, what a man ſhall do that ſcruples or doubts of the truth of any of the Articles, whether he may ſatisfie himſelf with ſuch an Interpretation before it be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95224:17"/>Authorized by a Convocation (or otherwiſe), I muſt anſwer that I apprehend a great deal of reaſon for it, but dare not paſs ſuch a determination. If <hi>I</hi> ſcruple any thing my ſelf <hi>I</hi> ſhall declare it, and unleſs <hi>I</hi> am ſatisfied in that ſenſe of the point as <hi>I</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve was the meaning of the Impoſers, <hi>I</hi> muſt fly to my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, not of an <hi>Interpretation,</hi> but of the liberty for <hi>Exception</hi> or <hi>Limitation,</hi> and that indeed does my work. This Scrupuloſity, and rigour of my mind for avoiding every thing of a Solemne lie (though never ſo ſmall) does make me wiſh for ſuch a <hi>Canon,</hi> or the allowance of a <hi>greater Authority,</hi> by ſome Act of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> will therefore now turn me to the Higher Powers, for I muſt beg their Pardon for this Endeavour of mine to make my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the Vineyard before they have opened the way for us, who can alone Legally do it. I would hereby, kindly provoke them to think at laſt on ſome Explanatory Act for Uniting the Proteſtant, and reſtoring the Ejected; who have now been out of our Livings above Fifteen year, and no evil we hope hath been found in us, beſides our preaching ſometimes, and praying, and the keeping of our Conſciences. And becauſe it is ſaid, common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Members of either Houſe, that if they knew what we would have, or thought we know our ſelves, they would do it; I cannot forbear to preſent them with the Materialls of ſuch a Bill, in telling them <hi>what we would have,</hi> from what is ſaid already; if they will but bear with the repetition. For when the obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch a bleſſing for the Nation is even near paſt my <hi>hopes,</hi> yet muſt it be ſtill in my <hi>prayers;</hi> I may not be wanting to it in my <hi>endeavours;</hi> and it cannot be beyond my <hi>Wiſhes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas then, there are many jealouſies aroſe about Popery (to frame a Preamble, as well as a body for ſuch a Bill out of what is before delivered,) which makes it even neceſſary to the peace of the Nation, that the Proteſtant intereſt be united and ſtrengthened by all good and lawfull means, and to this end there being this one proper expedient, to wit, the removing the occaſions of <hi>Diviſion</hi> which ſeveral perſons do find to themſelves in thoſe late injunctions which yet were intended to the ſame purpoſe of <hi>Concord</hi> in the Realm: <hi>That which we would have,</hi> is, that the Parliament would be pleaſed that a Bill be prepared for Peace and Union, which might bear ſome ſuch Title. <hi>An Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natory Act for agreement amongſt Proteſtants, and for Eaſe in the buſineſs in Religion.</hi> In which Bill I would have ſuch an Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95224:18"/>of theſe Impoſitions, and ſuch Alleviations in regard to the tenderly conſiderate, and peaceably Scrupulous, or, <hi>ſoberly,</hi> not <hi>factiouſly</hi> Conſciencious (who will never be wonne) as may do our buſineſs.</p>
            <p>In the Act of Uniformity, By the Declaration of <hi>Aſſent and Conſent to all things, and every thing, contained in, and preſcribed, by, the two book, of Common Prayer, and of Ordering Prieſts and Deacons,</hi> there is no conſiderate man of the Parliament ever (I hope) underſtood that theſe books are in every minute particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar infallible, or free from that defect which is incident to all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Compoſures; but they underſtand I ſuppoſe, that they are in the maine contents to be ſincerely approved and uſed: I <hi>would have</hi> it therefore be here ſufficient, if this Declaration be made to the uſe of the book in the Ordinary dayly Lords-day ſervice, which we can conſent to, or that we may make it with a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe of Exception againſt any matter or matters (out of that Service) which the Biſhop ſhall think meet to be diſpenſed with upon Convincing reaſon; Provided only that the Ordinary conſtant publick Service of the Liturgy obtains Conſent and Practiſe. And for the <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which are, and have been always, and on all hands held only for <hi>indifferent</hi> things, <hi>I wiſh</hi> they might be left to the <hi>Conſciences</hi> and prudence of Miniſters and People e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where (excepting the <hi>Cathedralls,</hi>) to <hi>uſe</hi> them, or <hi>forbear</hi> them as they judge it moſt meet for one anothers <hi>edification;</hi> for ſo ſome Biſhops I believe, if it be left to them, will ſometimes be apt to determine themſelves. Provided that if any perſon will have his child baptized with the ſigne of the Croſs, or ſtands upon any thing elſe hitherto required by the Service-book, if the Miniſter himſelf Scruple the performance, he ſhall always have ſome Aſſiſtant or Curate to do it.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Act, By the <hi>Subſcription,</hi> before treated, As I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve there was no new Ill or ſtrange thing intended by any of them, but the rightfull maintenance onely of the Kings authority againſt Rebellion: So do I apprehend that the Interpretation and the Limitations which I do here humbly preſent with an unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed impartiality upon the ſeveral Clauſes of it, may paſs their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick approbation or allowance; which therefore <hi>I would have</hi> to be done, as a matter of kind <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to <hi>moſt</hi> Mens conſciences, and of <hi>grievance</hi> to <hi>no</hi> Body. Onely for that part of it which is enjoyned but to the year 1682, it might do better perhaps to be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95224:18"/>made to ceaſe preſently, and be no longer impoſed.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as there is an Oath alſo in the Act of <hi>Oxford</hi> required of all Non conformiſt preachers that reſide ín any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate town, or come within five Miles of it, whereof I have Printed a former Paper, and given the <hi>Interpretation</hi> throughout as I believed it to be the very ſenſe and meaning onely of the Act, without <hi>limitation</hi> or <hi>exception,</hi> which cannot therefore be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, inſomuch as I dare, and do appeal to a Vote of the two Houſes whether I have delivered their minds or no: I would here have it onely put to the Queſtion; and if it be (as I doubt not) indeed their ſenſe, that they would declare it. This will make that Oath ſtreight be generally taken. Or elſe, I will propoſe this rather (which is better) that it may ſuffice any man to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the right of this free-born liberty to go where he will in his own Country, I mean to eſcape the penalty of this Act, and ſerve him alſo inſtead of the forementioned Subſcription, to take that Oath in this form of words following. <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>do ſwear, that I hold it unlawful upon any pretence to take Armes againſt the King, his Government, or Laws: And that I diſclaim that dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Poſition of taking Armes by his Authority againſt his Perſon, or any Legally commiſſionated by him in the Legal purſuit of ſuch Commiſſions: And that I will not endeavour any alteration of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the Church or State in any way or manner not warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Conſtitution of this Kingdom (that is in a ſeditious man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner), or any otherwiſe then by Act of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It being required moreover in the Act of uniformity (which is another of the things alſo before Mentioned) that every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter who enjoyes any Living ſhall be ordained by a Biſhop, and there are ſeveral perſons of late who in caſe of neceſſity for want of Biſhops took Presbyterian Orders, <hi>I would have</hi> the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment declare it their intent (for redeeming their credit with the Reformed Churches beyond the Seas), not to make it abſolutely neceſſary for ſuch perſons to be <hi>reordained to the Office,</hi> but that it may be enough for them if they receive this ſecond Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hands to the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of their Office in the <hi>New charge</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which they are, or ſhall be appointed, and that the Biſhop may, and ſhall frame his words accordingly. This is the only way that I could find out, for peace to my own mind (as I have told before) in this buſineſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas there is a Subſcription alſo in the Canons and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95224:19"/>Canonical Oath of Obedience impoſed on moſt Miniſters by the Biſhops (mentioned before likewiſe), which have given ſome of the greateſt occaſion to Non-conformiſts heretofore, and which yet have never paſſed into a Law by any Act of Parliament: I would here have it enquired by what Authorty <hi>one</hi> of theſe is impoſed, for I know none; And for <hi>that</hi> which is found in the Canons, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what is more than needs, becauſe included in other injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>I would have</hi> it Exauthorized, and that nothing more of this nature might be impoſed on us than is made neceſſary by the Act of the thirteenth of <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> Provided nevertheleſs, if the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop be unſatisfyed about any particular Perſon, he ſhall be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to offer a due acknowledgment of his reverence to Biſhops in a laudible Teſtimony thereof under his hand, and of his fair re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the main ſubſtance of the three Articles contained in that Canonicall Subſcription in ſuch expreſſions as ſhall beſt ſatisfy his own Conſcience, and be approved as ſufficient under the hands of two Epiſcopal Doctors, or allowed by the Biſhop.</p>
            <p>And in regard there hath bin great offence taken by conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Miniſters (which is a thing hath not yet bin mentioned) at the Biſhop, or his Courts commanding them to read then ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommunication againſt ſome or other of their Pariſh, for ſuch faults as they think not at all worthy of ſo great cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or elſe be exempted from the execution of that charge; and that the Biſhop or his Court provide ſome other perſon that is ſatisfied about it, to do it. And I would have none forced to give the Body and Blood of Chriſt to any, but to whom they can, in point of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place, To the intent that a free ſearch after Truth may be encouraged, and many other Scruples avoided upon that account: I would have them Authorize this one thing which I have offered, as more peculiar in this Paper; which is, That though an Authentick Interpretation, which is the Senſe and Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only of the Law-giver, be that Interpretation which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as the Subſtance of all Laws, ſeeing no <hi>Law,</hi> as no <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is <hi>of Private Interpretation:</hi> yet in all matters of Words merely and Phraſes, an Interpretation that is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſual,</hi> and in all <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles,</hi> or <hi>Theſes</hi> for Concord (which I diſtinguiſh from <hi>Laws</hi>) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion, and the <hi>Homilies</hi> of the Church, a <hi>Doctrinal</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95224:19"/>be ſufficient for an Aſſent or Subſcription to them.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the Things, and there is no leſs than theſe, and (I think) no more than theſe, which are neceſſary to reconcile the Moderate Conformiſt and Non-conformiſt, which is one Part of my Deſigne, and <hi>Accommodation.</hi> If they will pull out <hi>Nine</hi> Thorns out of our Feet, and leave a <hi>Tenth,</hi> we cannot go along with them. Be it reſolved therefore by the Grace of God, and both Houſes, that if any Perſon be willing to conform to the preſent Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and her Service appointed upon theſe, any of theſe, and every one of theſe Explanations, Allevia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Declarations, Lenitives, or Cautions, he ſhall be admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Preferment, and enjoy the uſe of his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry without Moleſtation. All Statutes, Canons, or Laws to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>To paſs now to the other part of this Bill or Deſigne, which is <hi>Indulgence;</hi> In the way, Becauſe the very Superintendency of Biſhops, and that Subjection to them which is required by the Conſtitution of the Realm is, or may be, an Hindrance to many ſober Miniſters, and other Proteſtants of coming into the Church, who are ready to conſent to the <hi>Doctrine,</hi> but not to the <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> of it, I would have them declare, That ſo long as any Perſon or Party do acknowledge the King's Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, as Head of the Church in this Nation, and obey their Ordinary <hi>in licitis &amp; honeſtis,</hi> upon the account of his Authority committed to the Biſhops, and their Officers, as Subſtitutes of his for the Exerciſe of that External Objective Regiment <hi>Circa Sacra,</hi> which is granted by all our Divines to the Higher Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in every Nation, it is much as is, or can be required in Law to the owning Epiſcopal Juriſdiction; and ſhall ſerve them to all Intents and Purpoſes, no leſs than a profeſſed Belief and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the immediate Divine Right of it. That is, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be ſome that cannot acknowledge our Dioceſan Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates to be Chriſt's Officers diſtinct from the <hi>Elders</hi> in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet ſo long as they can live peaceable Lives in Obedience to them, as Eccleſiaſtical Magiſtrates under his Majeſty for the keeping the ſeveral Congregations in their Precincts to that Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel-Order which themſelves allow, and for Superviſing their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions in things indifferent, that nothing be done but in Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bordination to the Peace of the Kingdome (which is a Notion wherein the Judicious of every Party may acquieſce) it is enough
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95224:20"/>for their Reception into National Church-Union. And this is ſo far from Derogating from the Biſhops Office and Dignity, that it were a way to be choſe in Policy to advance it; while it makes his Authority ſignificant to the Presbyterian, and Independent, as well as to the Miniſter that hath a Living; and rears him an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection</hi> over the <hi>Gathered,</hi> as over the <hi>Parochial</hi> Congregation.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch then, as there are moreover ſome Miniſters of a good Life, that cannot according to their Judgments allow of our Parochial Churches, nor the Book of Liturgy; but do chooſe to Worſhip God and Jeſus Chriſt in the way of their gathered or ſeparate Congregations, and crave the Protection and Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the King upon their Allegiance, as other Subjects en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy (the Conſcience being obnoxious to God only, and not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to be conſtrained by the Rigour of Laws, or by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treameſt Execution of them): If the Parliament-Men would know further what we would have, I <hi>would have</hi> theſe Men all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born and let alone, thinking this Advantage the Church-Men have over ſuch, to be enough, that <hi>they</hi> have the State-Countenance, and <hi>theſe</hi> are uncapable in their way of all Publick Emolument till they come into them.</p>
            <p>And to the intent the Forborn may be wrought upon by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Motives of their own Good, and at their own Time, I would have (as the other deſigned Part (I ſay) of ſuch a Bill) ſuch a Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Act of Grace be granted, that all and every Chriſtian-Subject throughout his Majeſty's Realms, that profeſs themſelves of the Reformed Religion, be pardoned all Faults and Penalties what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever incurred upon the account of any forepaſſed Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and that they ſhall not, during ſo many Years to come (as ſhall be Voted) be vexed or perſecuted any more for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, in the matter of Religion. Provided they commit not any heinous Crime worthy of Puniſhment, but carry themſelves Innocently and Peaceably, both with Submiſſion to all due Order in their <hi>own</hi> Churches, and without Diſturbance to the <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccléſiaſtical</hi> Government now ſetled in the Nation.</p>
            <p>There are theſe two Ingredients that are neceſſary to the Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of the Kingdom. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> and <hi>Liberty.</hi> Union is for ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Church</hi> for <hi>God:</hi> Liberty is for ſtrengthning the <hi>Land,</hi> for the <hi>King.</hi> There is Trade to be encouraged, and Wars to be Managed; and <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> ſerves theſe ends againſt our <hi>Civil Enemies</hi> in helping us to more hands; as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:95224:20"/>ſerves us againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and the <hi>Enemies</hi> of our <hi>Religion.</hi> And what indeed ſhould we do with our Brethren that differ from us in opinion? <hi>Shall we ſmite them?</hi> No, but <hi>ſet Bread and Water before them.</hi> Perſecution will make them more zealous and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine them, but liberty muſt brake them, or win them. They muſt have time. And if the naming what time may not be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and I may ſpeak who ſpake the reſt, I would ſet it during this Kings Reign, that ſo every Man may pray for his Life, and he may have the Title (more auguſtly) of <hi>Carolus Clemens</hi> when he dyes.</p>
            <p>And for the making our Union of better ſignification to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd, and more effectual prevention of that Scandall which is raiſed on the Clergy through the Covetouſneſs of ſome (A fault that we Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are taxed with generally, even when we ſeek but things juſt, and theſe therefore muſt take the more heed) who heap up to themſelves all the Preferments they can get, which are neither agreeable to their Labour, or their want; nor to the duty of that tremendous calling unto which they are called; but by this means, many other Miniſters are deprived even of neceſſary maintenance for their families, and an occaſion is adminiſtred to themſelves of pride (an undecent immeaſurable Exaltation above their rank and birth, to the envy of others), Of careleſneſs (through the impoſſibility of a due attendance on a double or trebble charge), Of more world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mindedneſs, a looſer life, and ſo of ill example of ten times unto their flocks, whereby the Souls of many Pariſhes (which ought to be more precious to the Miniſter than his Maintenance) are ſinfully neglected, to the offence of Almighty God, and the haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of their own, and their peoples Salvation: I <hi>would have no</hi> Clergy-man henceforward be ſuffered to enjoy any more than one Living, or Cure of Souls, and one Dignity at one time; and that every man without exception, that hath more than one of either, ſhould immediately give up the reſt to be diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted among thoſe who ſhall be <hi>Comprehended,</hi> or brought into the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Order.</hi> Which that they may alſo be obtained, and poſſeſſed with a clear Conſcience, and that grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Corruption of <hi>Simony</hi> may be extirpate out of the Land, I <hi>wiſh</hi> that Every Patron that ſhall hence forward preſent his Clerk to any Living, may have the Oath called the Simoniacall Oath impoſed on himſelf, no leſſe than on the Incumbent (which I perceive (ſince I writ this) is petitioned for by the Schollars of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95224:21"/>
               <hi>Oxford</hi>) and if he refuſes to take it, that then the Biſhop ſhould have immediate power (taking only the ſame Oath) of preſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in his Room.</p>
            <p>By ſuch Materialls as theſe put into the hands of a Skillfull workman, by the Order of our Maſter builders, and by ſuch a courſe, or courſes, as this, or theſe, thoroughly perſued, the name of the great God would be exceedingly honoured, in the integrity and ingenuity of thoſe Gentlemen who have Benefices in their dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; in the ſelf deny all of thoſe Miniſters who have Pluralities in in their poſſeſſion; in the reſtauration of ſeveral ejected painfull Laborers into the Vineyard; in the generall advancement of Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and that intereſt which is Heavenly, above worldly advantage; in the unity, peace, and mutual agreement of Brethren in the ſame function differing mainly in things indifferent; in the univerſall good will among the People; and in the eſtabliſhed Happineſs and Proſperity of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to future Generations. <hi>In that time ſhall the Preſent be brought unto the Lord of Hoſts, of a people ſcattered and peeled, meeted out, and troden under foot, to the place of the Name of the Lord of Hoſts, Mount</hi> Zion.</p>
            <closer>Deo Gloria Authori Condonatio.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <head>An Advertiſement</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> I thought here to Reprint my Paper about the <hi>Oxford-Oath,</hi> which ſeems to be made neceſſary by my Reference to it <hi>(p. 31.):</hi> but becauſe the Matter thereof is incident with that of the Subſcription, I ſuppoſe it may be ſpared. I muſt ſignifie alſo, that whereas I have dropt the two Letters of my Name in reference to my Subſcription (in <hi>p. 19.</hi>): I cannot, and I do not let it go, as one that is a preſent Actual Subſcriber, but as one under Deliberation to proceed (or not) as I can, and no otherwiſe than I can, according to my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with the flow haſt of others Advice, and my own ſetled Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:95224:21"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THis Paper being a Countermine againſt Popery, I do think fit to haſten it out, that the Members of Parliament may have compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent time to conſider of it this Seſſion. I did not think the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Part would have been ſo ſeaſonable, as I humbly believe it may be now to the moſt of thoſe who deſire a long Life for the King, and the Growth of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion. It was almoſt Deſpair ſet me on the Work, and now there is a little Hope got into my Heart, that ſomething may come of this Endeavour, and God's Bleſſing be upon it. The Reaſon why I annex this Half Sheet to the reſt, is becauſe I find it neceſſary in regard to that one Clauſe in the Subſcription, <hi>And that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawful Oath.</hi> I deſire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der here to remember, that I ſubſcribe not this Clauſe by vertue of an <hi>Interpretation,</hi> for I think the meaning of the Law giver to be more then I can ſubſcribe unto: but by virtue of my Liberty of <hi>Exception</hi> and <hi>Reſtriction.</hi> I do therefore diſtinguiſh between the <hi>Matter Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> which is the Extirpation of Prelacy, or Change of Government: and the <hi>Act of Covenanting,</hi> which was their ſwearing to endeavour it. I would have the Reader then note alſo, that I ſubſcribe not that the Oath in the Matter Covenanted was in it ſelf unlawful: for this Matter Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanted (I have ſaid) may be conſidered <hi>Preciſely</hi> in it ſelf, or <hi>Complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> with its Circumſtances, and more particularly under the Circumſtance of the King's Remonſtrances againſt the Covenant. I do believe, that an Endeavour of any Alteration of Government under this Circumſtance of the King's Prohibitions that is, for any to go about it without his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and againſt it (as I ſpeak) was <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawfull, though I ſuppoſe it not ſo under the contrary Circumſtances (if the King had allowed it), and conſequently that it is not <hi>ſo in its ſelf,</hi> if we reſpect onely this Matter Covenanted: But for as much as an <hi>Act</hi> becomes <hi>Evil</hi> upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Defect, when all Circumſtances muſt concur to make an Action Good, and he that ſwore this Covenant could not ſwear to the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Preciſely,</hi> but <hi>Complexly</hi> conſidered, that is, to the Matter under this Circumſtance with others, I do apprehend that the matter being thereby render'd evil, the Oath as taken for the <hi>Act of Covenanting,</hi> in regard to this Circumſtance was <hi>in it ſelf unlawful.</hi> It may be plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Covenant maintaines the King and his Authority to the full, and limits this Endeavour to mens Places and Callings, and that there was therefore nothing in this unlawfull. I reply, If any man ſhould
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95224:22"/>argue rather, that the ſupream Power of this Nation does lie in the King and the Parliament as one Corporation, and when they were divided (and the Parliament could not be diſſolved) the Conſtitution was at an end, or <hi>Interſtition;</hi> That conſequently every one, &amp; any one, might covenant, at that time, to ſet up a new Government without the conſent of Either, King or Parliament, by the way of an <hi>Agreement of the People,</hi> This were to ſay ſomething: But to own the King and his Authority, and ſwear to maintain it in the ſame Oath, wherein they ſwear to change the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (when he declares againſt that Change, that is) without him, and againſt his Authority, this is vertually a contradiction in <hi>Adjecto,</hi> and makes the Oath in the very act it ſelf of ſwearing (if that be, or may go for, the Oath <hi>in it ſelf</hi>) unlawful. Again, To ſwear that <hi>in our place and calling,</hi> we will endeavour to change the Government when the King refuſes his conſent, What is it, but to ſwear to do that, in the doing whereof we muſt Act <hi>out of our Place and Calling,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is, and can be, no Endeavour of that kind <hi>in our Place and Calling,</hi> but what is done with Subordination to his Conſent in an Act of Parliament? You will ſay perhaps, It is true, that they entred this Covenant without the King<hi>'s</hi> Conſent, but the Meaning of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was, That the Change ſhould be made, and endeavoured to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected only by his Conſent. I return, To enter into Covenant to Change the Government when the King by his Remonſtrances and Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons did declare that he would not conſent to that Change, and prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited his Subjects to enter into ſuch a League, was I ſuppoſe in it ſelf <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful. Or thus, To Swear againſt the King<hi>'s</hi> Will or Prohibition to do a thing which to do without his Will is unlawful, is in it ſelf. (I take it) an unlawful Oath. Such was this Covenant. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, It is too well known that it was the <hi>Scots</hi> brought in this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and that it is (or was) a Principle of theirs, That the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Religion belongs to the <hi>Kirk,</hi> ſo as they may (or might) ſet it up, or endeavour the ſame without the Conſent of the King, if they obtain it not (which is a Principle in my Apprehenſion directly repugnant to that Supreamacy which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Subjects give to their <hi>King</hi>), and it was apparent, that the Covenant was carried on by the Parliament and Army according to that Principle; ſo that if any pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly judicious Man ſhall ſcruple his Soul with the Belief that this was the Meaning of the Oath, That they ſhould endeavour a Reformation to be effected only by the King<hi>'s</hi> Conſent, and not otherwiſe, I have two things to offer him for his Conviction; to wit, The conſtant Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the Covenanters to the contrary, and this one Argument, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95224:22"/>alone I ſhall reſt. To ſwear to endeavour a Change of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment when the King refuſes his Conſent, muſt either be with Intention to do it without his Conſent, or elſe be a vain Oath. But to do this in a diſorderly way without his Conſent, or to take the Oath in vain, either of the two, was in it ſelf (I ſuppoſe) <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful. <hi>Ergo,</hi> This Oath <hi>was in ſelf an unlawful Oath.</hi> I would not have any of my Brethren therefore here to be ſtumbled (as they are apt to be) ſo ſoon as they diſcry the Scope of this Subſcription to tend to a Renunciation of the Covenant; for if we may be permitted to Renounce this Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with this Liberty of <hi>Exception</hi> of what is Good and Obligatory in it, and <hi>Reſtriction</hi> of the Renunciation to that only which is <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful,</hi> as the Endeavour of any Alteration of Government in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly way, without the Conſent of the King (as they did in the late times) was, I ſee no reaſon why they ſhould not be as forward to ſuch a Renunciation, as to any other the like Injunction. For my own part, to rid my ſelf of this Scruple quite, which in regard to the Words <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> have been apt to ſtick upon me ſtill in this Clauſe, I will conclude thus. If the meaning of the covenant by <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring the extirpation of Prelacy,</hi> was only to endeavour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Church in ſubordination to the Conſent of the King with his Parliament, I put in my <hi>exception</hi> againſt the Clauſe: but if the intent of it was to have us endeavour any ſuch thing without his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and againſt it, as the practiſe of the Covenanters did ſhew, and as it was generally (I think) underſtood, I do Subſcribe to this Clauſe, <hi>And that the ſame was in it ſelf an unlawful Oath,</hi> as I do to the reſt, with my Liberty of Limitation. It is but an honeſt thing (I judge) for me, and others (if they will follow), to do what we can; and ſo long as I do no more than I can, I ſhall not (I hope) hurt my Conſcience. If the Biſhop will be contented with this Rule, and we be alſo contented with it, what ſhall binder our Concord? When the Miniſters of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Policy have ſo long been hatching up Sects amongſt us, and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting our Diviſions, and even now plodding at one Thruſt, or one Blow (if Fame have any more in her Trumpet than Sound only) the general Deſtruction of our Religion, it is time (or there is Reaſon), for the Parliament to think on <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion; or for the Biſhops and us, to come to Compoſition. <hi>Then</hi> Abner <hi>called to</hi> Joab, <hi>and ſaid, ſhall the Sword devour for ever? Knoweſt thou not that it will be Bitterneſs in the latter End? How long ſhall it be then ere thou bid the People return from following of their Brethren?</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The Author.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:95224:23"/>
            <head>Some further Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>LEt the <hi>Reader</hi> note, that where I ſpeak ſtill of all Endeavour to change the Government without the Conſent of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Authority to be unlawful, I underſtand it of that Change altogether that is Publick, and concerns the Church as National. I meddle not with Reformation otherwiſe. I alſo Advertiſe the <hi>Reader,</hi> (ſeeing I have a Side to ſpare) That it hath bin in my thoughts (I muſt needs tell him) ever ſince the <hi>Ejecting Act,</hi> to offer ſomething (the beſt I could) for our Rulers Condeſcention to our Scruples: and for our Submiſſion to their Laws. That is to be Equal on both ſides. As I have formerly therefore ſent out ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Papers on the Firſt Errand; Here is two ſent now upon the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. My Paper about the <hi>Oxford-Oath,</hi> and this Paper. I have ſome Sheets more by me (under Twenty) that carry Things a little Higher, if not quite Home; and I could not let them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore come out, till this Paper ſhould make their Way for them. They have bin long ready, and bin ſeen by many, as Biſhop <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins,</hi> Judge <hi>Hales,</hi> and the like Temperate Perſons. I ſhall Entitle thoſe Sheets, <hi>A Peaceable Reſolution of Conſcience concerning our preſent Impoſitions.</hi> When that Book alſo is come abroad (out of which I have bin borrowing ſomething or other ſtill for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Books that ſince paſſed from me) I ſhall have accompliſhed my Purpoſe, and intend to have done for ever about theſe Matters. I muſt add, that I have juſt now Received this enſuing Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <head>To my Honoured Friend, Mr. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> in <hi>Oxenden</hi>-Street.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I <hi>Thank you heartily for your Kindneſs, in ſending my your</hi> Healing Paper <hi>ſo ſpeedily. This Day I received it, and red it to my great Satisfaction. I fully agree with the Rule which you have laid down in order to Peace and Concord; and judg, that in the whole Management of the Deſgine, you have done Honeſtly and Prudently. I firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion by a reaſonable Accommodation, is Religions Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest. The Relaxation that would ſuffice you, I think would ſuffice me. In the Terms of Conformity as explained and limited by you, with whoſe neceſſary Reſtrictions, there is no material Difference between you and me, as I diſcern. <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                           <desc> _____ </desc>
                        </gap> My carneſt Prayer is, that God would proſper this your Deſigne of Peace; And I am much perſwaded, that Good will come of it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Chicheſter, <date>Octob. 12. 1678.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Obliged and Affectionate Friend &amp; Servant, <hi>John Corbet.</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
